人人影视
原创翻译  双语字幕
字幕组招新中
请访问 yysub.cc
翻译    核平考研小罐头 彼岸的宁静 斗斗
翻译    VioletCheng 爵士年代蓬蓬裙
翻译    前尘隔海 陈奥奥 令狐伟
翻译    辰星晓Reginamoon 潇然 凌波
翻译    点心mumu 茕茕荧惑 易碎的绝对
校对    杏仁斯嘉丽
鸣谢    草草 小酸奶
时间轴    噃噃bobo 大葱 DA
时间轴    壬虚浪影 罗大 无关风粤
后期    吉吉
总监    杏仁斯嘉丽
普罗米修斯从天神处盗取火焰  将其赠予人类
他因此被锁链绑在巨石上  永生永世遭受折磨
裂变
聚变
氰化钾
《荒原》
T·S·艾略特著
语出爱因斯坦
普遍认为这代表
他反对量子力学及其随机性
放射性实验室
周六两点  西班牙忠诚派集会
原子分裂释放两亿伏电
希特勒入侵波兰
"胜利或战死"
城市被炸  但泽沦陷
放射性实验室成立工会
联邦调查局
放射性实验室
洛斯阿拉莫斯项目正门
讨论会
那个装置对文明的影响
T-31楼  周日11点  洛斯阿拉莫斯
在岗哨停车  查验身份权限
《时代》
原子弹之父
奥本海默  头号原子能思想家
杜鲁门宣布氢弹计划
施特劳斯上将生日快乐
施特劳斯事件  参议院对抗总统
《时代》
路易斯·施特劳斯
原子能委员会总负责人  K·D·尼科斯
奥本海默
奥本海默博士
Dr. Oppenheimer.
在我们开始前  我相信你想要宣读一份声明
As we begin, I believe you have a statement to read into the record.
是的  法官大人
Yes, your honor.
-我们不是法官  博士  -我明白
- We're not judges, Doctor. - No.
你们当然不是
Of course.
各位安全委员会的成员
Members of the security board,
在你们对我的起诉书中提到的所谓审讯信息
the so-called interrogatory information in your indictment of me
必须要结合我的工作与生活
cannot be fairly understood
才能被公正地理解
except in the context of my life, and my work.
他作证了多久
How long did he testify?
说实话  我忘了
Honestly, I forget.
整个听证会进行了一个月
The whole hearing took a month.
-简直是磨难  -我只读过文字记录
- An ordeal. - Oh, I've only read the transcripts.
-谁会想为自己的一生辩护呢  -你当时不在吗
- Who'd want to justify their whole life? - You weren't there?
作为主席  我不能参加
As chairman, I wasn't allowed to be.
他们真的会问这事吗
Are they really going to ask about it?
这已经是很多年前了
It was years ago.
-是四年前的事  -五年了
- Four years ago. - Five.
奥本海默仍然让美国分裂
Oppenheimer still divides America.
委员会肯定会问起你当时的立场的
The committee's going to want to know where you stood.
瑟蒙德参议员让我转告你  不要觉得自己在受审
Senator Thurmond asked me to say not to feel that you're on trial.
说来有趣  我本来没觉得  直到你提起
Oh, funny. I didn't, until you just said that.
-真的  施特劳斯先生  -是上将
- Really, Mr. Strauss... - It's Admiral.
上将  施特劳斯上将  这只是走个形式
Admiral. Admiral Strauss, this is a formality.
艾森豪威尔总统已经邀请您加入他的内阁
President Eisenhower has asked you to be in his cabinet.
参议院除了顺从他  别无选择
The Senate really has no choice but to confirm him.
那如果他们提起奥本海默呢
And if they bring up Oppenheimer?
如果他们提起奥本海默  你就如实回答
When they bring up Oppenheimer, you answer honestly,
你履行了职责  这一点没有任何参议员能否认
no senator can deny you did your duty.
只是会有点令人不适
It'll be uncomfortable.
毕竟谁会想为自己的一生辩护呢
Who'd want to justify their whole life?
你当初为什么离开美国
Why did you leave the United States?
我想去学最新的物理知识
I... I wanted to study the new physics.
在这里不能学吗
Was there nowhere here?
伯克利不就有一流的理论物理系吗
I thought Berkeley had the leading theoretical physics department.
是的  那是我创立的
Yes, once I built it.
但在那之前我得先去欧洲
But first I had to go to Europe.
我去了剑桥  师从帕特里克·布莱克特
I went to Cambridge, to study under Patrick Blackett.
比起在美国  你在那里是不是更开心
Were you happier there than in America?
-更开心  -没错
- Happier? - Yes.
不
No.
不  我当时
No, I, uh...
我当时很想家
I was homesick and...
情绪上也不成熟
emotionally immature...
总能看到某个隐藏的宇宙  因此深受困扰
Troubled by visions of a... hidden universe.
我在实验室一无是处
Useless in the lab.
天哪  奥本海默
Christ, Oppenheimer.
你昨晚没睡吗
Have you had any sleep?
重来
Start again.
我得去听讲座  老师
I need to go to a lecture, sir.
至于吗
Why?
是尼尔斯·玻尔的讲座
It's Niels Bohr.
我忘得一干二净
I completely forgot.
好了  咱们走
Alright! Let's go.
不  你不能去  奥本海默
Oh no, not you, Oppenheimer.
你镀完板子再走
You finish coating those plates.
量子物理不是向前迈出的一步
Quantum physics is not a step forward.
而是一种理解现实的全新方式
It is a new way to understand reality.
爱因斯坦打开了大门
Einstein's opened the door.
让人得以窥视我们所生活的世界中的另一个世界
Now we are peering through, seeing a world inside our world,
那里充斥着能量和悖论  并非所有人都能接受
a world of energy and paradox that not everyone can accept.
你没事吧
You alright?
尼尔斯  这位是J·罗伯特·奥本海默
Nils, meet J. Robert Oppenheimer.
J代表什么
What's the J stand for?
没什么
Nothing, apparently.
你去听了我的讲座  问了全场唯一一个好问题
You were at my lecture. You asked the only good question.
没人否认他的洞察力
No one's denying his insight.
但他的实验室工作还有一些不足
It's his laboratory work that leaves a little to be desired.
我听说你之前也是那样回答的
I heard you give the same answer...
在哈佛  没错  而你问了同样的问题
At Harvard, yes, and you asked the same question.
为什么又问一遍
Why ask again?
我不喜欢你之前的回答
I hadn't liked your answer.
-那你对昨天的回答还满意吗  -很满意
- Did you like it better yesterday? - A lot.
即便没准备好应付石头下的蛇  你也可以抬起它
You can lift a stone without being ready for the snake that's revealed.
现在你似乎已经准备好了
Now it seems you're ready.
但你在实验室并不开心
But you don't enjoy the lab.
所以离开剑桥吧  离开那些烧杯和药水
So get out of Cambridge, with its beakers and potions.
去一个能让你思考的地方
Go somewhere they'll let you think.
是哪里呢
Where?
-哥廷根  -玻恩
- Göttingen. - Born.
玻恩
Born.
去德国  跟着马克斯·玻恩学习理论物理
Get to Germany, study under Max Born, learn the ways of theory.
我会跟他打招呼的
I'll send word.
有虫眼
Worm hole.
你的数学怎么样
How's your mathematics?
还没好到能支持他成为他想成为的物理学家
Not good enough for the physicist he wants to be.
代数就像乐谱
Algebra's like sheet music,
重要的不是你识不识谱  而是你能否听到音乐
the important thing isn't can you read music, it's can you hear it.
你能听到音乐吗  罗伯特
Can you hear the music, Robert?
是的  我能
Yes, I can.
怀俄明州参议员
The senator from Wyoming.
施特劳斯上将
Admiral Strauss,
我对您和J·罗伯特·奥本海默博士的关系很感兴趣
I'm interested in your relationship with Dr. J. Robert Oppenheimer.
你们在1947年相识
You met him in 1947.
是的
Correct.
你当时是原子能委员会的委员
You were a commissioner of the Atomic Energy Commission.
是的  但我与罗伯特认识时
I was, but I actually met Robert in my capacity
我的身份是普林斯顿高等研究院的董事会成员
as board member of the Institute for Advanced Study at Princeton.
当时
It was...
正值战后  他已经是世界知名的伟大物理学家
after the war, he was world-renowned as the great man of physics,
我决心请他执掌研究院
and I was determined to get him to run the Institute.
奥本海默博士  幸会
Dr. Oppenheimer. An honor.
你好  施特拉斯先生
Mr. Strauss.
应该是"施特劳斯"
It's pronounced "Strauss".
不管是"欧本海默"还是"奥本海默"
"Oppenheimer", "Oppenheimer"...
随便怎么读  对方都知道我是犹太人
Either way you say it, they know I'm Jewish.
我是曼哈顿以马内利会堂的会长
I'm president of Temple Emanu-El in Manhattan.
叫"施特劳斯"只是遵从南方的发音习惯而已
"Strauss" is just a Southern pronunciation.
总之  欢迎来到研究院  你在这应该会过得很开心
Anyway, welcome to the Institute. I think you'll be very happy here.
这里的通勤也很方便
Yes, well, you'll love the commute.
那栋房子就是为入职后的你准备的  你和你的妻子
The position comes with that house for you and your wife,
还有  两个孩子对吗
and your... is it two children?
没错  两个孩子
Yes, two.
我很敬仰你的工作
I'm a great admirer of your work.
你是科班出身的物理学家吗  施特劳斯先生
You're a physicist by training, Mr. Strauss?
抱歉  这里是公共休息室  茶点时间是四点
I'm sorry, uh, common room, four o'clock tea.
不  我没受过专业物理学训练
No, I'm not trained in physics or anything else.
我都是自学的
I'm a self-made man.
可以理解
Ah, I can relate to that.
-是吗  -我父亲也是
- Really? - Yes, my father was one.
这里就是你的办公室
And this would be your office.
听说下午他一般都在那里
I'm told he's there in most afternoons.
其实我一直很好奇
You know, I've always wondered
为什么你没有邀请他参加曼哈顿计划
why you didn't involve him in the Manhattan Project.
毕竟他是我们这个时代最伟大的科学家
Greatest scientific mind of our time.
是他那个时代
Of his time.
爱因斯坦发表相对论
Einstein published his Theory of Relativity
已经是40多年前的事了
more than 40 years ago now.
但他永远无法接受它所揭示的量子世界
Could never embrace the quantum world it revealed.
"上帝不会掷骰子"
"God doesn't play dice."
没错
Precisely.
你从没想过系统地学习物理吗  施特劳斯先生
You never thought of studying physics formally, Mr. Strauss?
曾有大学想录取我  但我选择了去卖鞋
I had offers, but... I chose to sell shoes.
路易斯·施特劳斯曾是个卑微的卖鞋人
Lewis Strauss was once a lowly shoe salesman.
不  就是个卖鞋人
No, just a shoe salesman.
-我很乐意介绍你们认识  -不必
- I'd love to introduce you. - No need.
我和他已经相识多年了
I've known him for years.
阿尔伯特
Albert.
他怎么那样  你对他说了什么
What was that? What did you say to him?
他没事
Oh, he's fine.
施特劳斯先生  我的一些过去  我想你有必要了解
Mr. Strauss, there are... things in my past you ought to be aware of.
作为原子能协会的主席
Well, as chairman of the AEC,
我已经读过了你的安全档案
I have access to your security file. I've read it.
-你不担忧吗  -不
- You're not worried? - No.
你已经为国家贡献了这么多  我有什么可担忧的
Why would I be worried, after everything you've done for your country?
时代变了  施特劳斯先生
Well, times change, Mr. Strauss.
这个研究院成立的目的
Well, the purpose of this institute
就是为独立思考的人才提供一个避难所
is to provide a haven for independent minds.
也就是你这种人
That's you.
这份工作  你是完美人选
You are the man for the job.
容我考虑一下
Well, then I'll consider it.
明天原子能委员会的例会上见吧
I'll see you at the AEC meeting tomorrow.
这是本国声望最高的职位之一
This is one of the most prestigious appointments in the country.
是的  而且通勤也很方便
Yes, and a great commute.
所以我才在考虑
That's why I'm considering it.
所以奥本海默博士在你任命他前  就已经提醒过你
So Dr. Oppenheimer brought your attention to his past associations
关于他过去结识的人的问题
before you appointed him?
是的
Yes.
而当时这并没有引起你的注意
And they didn't concern you?
当时我一心琢磨
Just then I was entirely consumed with
他到底对爱因斯坦说了什么  后者才对我没好气
what he must have said to Einstein to sour him on me.
那之后呢
But later?
之后发生的事  我们都很清楚
Well, we all know what happened later.
博士  你在欧洲的这段时间
Doctor, your time in Europe,
似乎认识了很多别国的物理学家
you seem to meet with a wide range of other countries' physicists.
是的  没错
Yes, that's right.
有苏联人吗
Any Russians?
据我所知应该没有
None that spring to mind.
-请允许我继续读我的声明...  -罗伯先生
- If you'll just allow me to continue with my statement... - Mr. Robb,
你会有足够的机会交叉询问的
you'll have ample opportunity to cross-examine.
离开哥廷根后  我搬到了荷兰的莱顿
After Göttingen, I moved on to Leiden, in Holland,
在那里我第一次见到了伊西多·拉比
where I first met Isidor Rabi.
借过
Excuse me.
一个美国佬来讲最新的物理学知识
A yank. Lecturing on the new physics.
这我可得听听
This I have to hear.
毕竟我就是美国人
I'm an American myself.
真是令人惊讶呢
How surprising.
如果他说的英语你有哪里听不懂  尽可以问我
Let me know if you need any help with the English.
α粒子和原子撞击
Bij de botsing tussen een alfadeeltje en een atoom,
此过程中产生的能量  特别是相对平移能
veranderen de verschillende energieën de verbindingssoort,
-会改变键能  -等等  他说的什么
- met name in de relatieve translatie. - Wait, what's he saying?
不用了  谢谢
No, thank you.
到苏黎世的路很远
It's a long way to Zurich.
你再瘦一点的话
If you get any skinnier,
就掉进坐垫缝里了
we're gonna lose you between the seat cushions.
-我是拉比  -奥本海默
- I'm Rabi. - Oppenheimer.
我听了你关于分子的讲座
I caught your lecture on molecules.
听懂了一部分
Caught some of it.
我俩都是纽约来的犹太人  为什么你懂荷兰语
We're a couple of New York Jews, how do you know Dutch?
我这学期到这里的时候  觉得还是最好学一下
Well, I thought I'd better learn it when I got here this semester.
你用六周  就把荷兰语学到了
You learned enough Dutch in six weeks
能讲量子力学课的程度
to give a lecture on quantum mechanics?
我喜欢挑战自我
I like to challenge myself.
量子物理还不够挑战是吧
Quantum physics wasn't challenging enough.
-爱炫耀  -什么意思
- Shvitzer. - Shvitzer?
说你爱出风头
Show-off.
虽然你六周就学会了荷兰语  但你不懂意第绪语
Dutch in six weeks, but you never learned Yiddish.
纽约我们那一区可没什么人说这种语言
They don't speak it so much my side of the park.
去你的
Screw you.
-你想家吗  -你懂的
- You homesick? - Oh, you know it.
你有没有觉得我们这种人在这边不太受欢迎
Ever get the feeling our kind isn't entirely welcome here?
你说物理学家吗
Physicists?
-真好笑  -在系里没觉得
- That's funny. - Not in the department.
他们也全是犹太人
They're all Jewish, too.
吃吧
Eat.
你必须去找那个德国人
There's this German you have to seek out.
-海森堡  -对
- Heisenberg. - Right.
人们可能会认为  在量子世界的背后
One might be led to the presumption that behind the quantum world
仍然隐藏着一个存在因果关系的真实世界
there still hides a real world in which causality holds,
但直白说  这种猜测在我们看来做不出成果
but such speculations seem to us, to say it explicitly, fruitless.
谢谢  祝各位今天愉快
Thank you. Have a great day.
-太好了  -谢谢
- Wonderful. - Thank you.
-奥本海默博士  -奥本海默  没错
- Dr. Oppenheimer. - Oppenheimer, yes!
我喜欢你关于分子的论文
I liked your paper on molecules.
很可能是因为你启发了我
Probably because you inspired it.
如果我还给了你其他启发  不妨告诉我
If I inspire anything else, let me know.
我们可以一起发表
We could publish together.
-我必须回美国  -为什么
- I have to get back to America. - Why?
那里没人把量子力学当回事
There's no one there taking quantum mechanics seriously.
正是这个原因
That's exactly why.
他想念曼哈顿的峡谷
He's pining for the canyons of Manhattan.
是新墨西哥州的峡谷
Canyons of New Mexico.
-你来自新墨西哥州吗  -不  纽约
- You're from New Mexico? - No, New York.
但我弟弟和我在圣达菲郊外有一个牧场
But my brother and I have a ranch outside Santa Fe.
此刻我想念那样的美国
That's the America I miss right now.
那就回家吧  两位牛仔
Then it's best you get home, cowboys.
他才是
That's him.
我和马
No, me and horses?
我可不喜欢
I don't think so.
很高兴认识你
Nice to meet you.
你后来还见过海森堡吗
Did you ever encounter Heisenberg again?
没会过面  不过
Not in person, no, but...
我们的人生算是有过交集
you might say our paths crossed.
回到美国后
On returning to America,
我同时在加州理工和伯克利任教
I accepted positions at both Caltech and up at Berkeley.
是劳伦斯博士吧
Dr. Lawrence, I presume?
你一定是奥本海默
You must be Oppenheimer.
是的
Yes.
我听说你想开设量子理论学院
I hear you want to start a school of quantum theory.
没错  就在隔壁
I am starting it, next door.
-他们安排的吗  -我申请的
- They put you in there? - I asked for it.
想离你们实验物理学家更近一些
Wanted to be close to you experimentalists.
理论是有局限的
Theory will get you only so far.
我们正在造一台加速电子的机器
We're building a machine to accelerate electrons.
了不起
Magnificent.
你愿意帮忙吗
Would you like to help?
帮忙造它  不了  不了
Build it? Oh, no. No, no.
但我愿意用它检验我正在研究的理论
But I am working on theories I'd like to test with it.
你什么时候开始教书
When do you start teaching?
一小时后开始上第一节课
I've got my first in an hour.
-研讨课吗  -一个学生
- Seminar? - Pupil.
一个学生  就一个吗
One student? That's it?
我教的是这里没人敢想的东西
I'm teaching something no one here has dreamt of.
但一旦人们知道你能用它做什么
But once people start hearing what you can do with it...
就不可能回头了
There's no going back.
-我一定是错过了...  -洛马尼茨先生
- Oh, I must have missed the... - Mr. Lomanitz?
-是我  -对  就是这里
- Yeah. - Yes, this is it.
请坐
Please, take a seat.
你对量子力学了解多少
What do you know about quantum mechanics?
我掌握了基础知识
I have a grasp on the basics.
那你就做错了
Then you're doing it wrong.
生命是由粒子还是波构成的
Is life made up of particles or waves?
量子力学说两者都是
Quantum mechanics says it's both.
怎么可能两者都是呢
How can it be both?
-不可能  -不可能
- It can't. - It can't.
但的确如此
But it is.
自相矛盾  但是成立
It's paradoxical, and yet, it works.
谢谢
Thank you.
洛马尼茨先生  你不会有事的
Mr. Lomanitz. You're gonna be okay.
斯奈德先生
Mr. Snyder.
想象一颗恒星
Now, let's consider a star.
恒星  在外太空中燃烧的巨大熔炉
A star, a vast furnace burning in outer space,
火焰克服自身的引力向外推  保持平衡
fire pushing outwards against its own gravity, balanced.
但是如果那个熔炉冷却了
But if that furnace cools,
引力开始占据上风  它会收缩
and gravity starts winning, it contracts.
-密度增加  -对
- Density increases. - Correct.
-引力增强  -密度增加
- Increasing gravity. - Increasing density.
-然后呢  -这是一个恶性循环  直到
- And? - It's a vicious cycle until...
何时会达到极限
What's the limit here?
我不知道  看看数学怎么回答
I don't know. See where the math takes us.
我保证这是一个没人探索过的领域
I guarantee it's somewhere no one's been before us.
我吗
Me?
对  你  你的数学比我好
Yes, you. Your math is better than mine.
奥本海默博士的档案
Dr. Oppenheimer's file
包含了他在伯克利活动的细节
contained details of his activities at Berkeley.
为什么战前就建了他的档案
Why would they have started a file on Dr. Oppenheimer before the war?
你得去问胡佛先生
Well, you'd have to ask Mr. Hoover.
我在问你  施特劳斯上将
I'm asking you, Admiral Strauss.
我猜测
Uh, my assumption
这和他参与
is that it was connected to his, uh,
左翼的政治活动有关
left-wing political activities.
你不应该让他们把政治带进课堂  奥比
You shouldn't let them bring their politics in the classroom, Oppie.
那是我写的
I wrote that.
劳伦斯  你欣然接受了物理学的革命
Lawrence, you embraced the revolution in physics.
却看不到别处的革命吗
Can't you see it everywhere else?
毕加索  斯特拉文斯基  弗洛伊德  马克思
Picasso, Stravinsky, Freud, Marx.
这是美国  奥比  我们经历过革命了
Well, this is America, Oppie. We had our revolution.
说真的  别带进实验室来
Seriously, keep it out of the lab.
好吧  实验室外
Well, out of the lab
我的女房东今晚要办小组讨论
my landlady is having a discussion group tonight.
感兴趣吗
Interested?
我随机调查过伯克利的政治圈子
I have sampled the Berkeley political scene.
全是哲学研究生和共产主义者
It's all just philosophy post-grads and communists
讨论取消种族隔离
talking integration.
你不关心取消种族隔离这件事吗
You don't care about integration?
我想投票支持  不想张嘴讨论
I want to vote for it, not talk about it.
今天周五就更不想了  来吧  吃饭去
Especially on a Friday. Come on, let's eat.
我弟弟到时候也会去
I'm meeting my brother there.
这些活动是如何引起了联调局的注意呢
And how would these activities have come to the attention of the FBI?
如果我没记错的话
Well, if I remember correctly,
在数次疑似共产主义者集会外
the FBI was taking license plates
联调局抄写了车牌号
outside suspected communist gatherings,
他的名字就浮现了
and his name popped up.
-天哪  -抱歉
- Jesus Christ! - Sorry.
弗兰克
Frank!
-你记得杰姬吗  -晚上好
- Uh, you remember Jackie? - Evening.
罗伯特  我想给你介绍薛瓦利埃
Robert! I want you to meet Chevalier.
哈康·薛瓦利埃博士  罗伯特·奥本海默博士
Dr. Haakon Chevalier, Dr. Robert Oppenheimer.
-幸会  -幸会
- Pleasure. - Pleasure.
这是我的弟弟弗兰克
This is my little brother, Frank.
-这位是...  -还是杰姬
- And this is... - Still Jackie.
你好  "还是杰姬"
Hello, Still Jackie.
薛瓦利埃  你在语言学院吗
Chevalier, you're in languages?
而你声名在外
And your reputation precedes you.
你听说了什么
What have you heard?
说你在教一种我不可能理解的
That you're teaching a radical new approach to physics
全新的物理学方法
I have no chance of understanding,
但我没听说你是党员
but I haven't heard you're a party member.
-我不是  -目前还不是
- Uh, I'm not. - Oh, not yet.
我和弗兰克在考虑入党
Frank and I are thinking of joining.
-前几天我还说呢...  -我支持很多事业
- Just the other day I was saying... - I support a range of causes.
西班牙内战
Spanish Civil War?
法西斯暴徒推翻了民主共和国
A democratic republic being overthrown by fascist thugs.
-谁不支持呢  -我们的政府
- Who wouldn't? - Our government.
他们认为社会主义比法西斯主义更具威胁
They think that socialism is a bigger threat than fascism.
很快就不会了  看看纳粹是怎么对犹太人的
Not for long. Look at what the Nazis are doing to the Jews.
我给德国的同事汇款  助其移民国外
I send funds to colleagues in Germany to emigrate.
我必须做点什么
I have to do something.
我自己的研究...太抽象了
My own work is so... abstract.
你在研究什么
What are you working on?
恒星死后会发生什么
What happens to stars when they die?
恒星会死吗
Do stars die?
如果恒星死亡  它们会冷却  接着坍缩
Well, if they do, they'd cool, then collapse.
实际上  恒星越大
In fact, the bigger the star,
它们的终结越为猛烈
the more violent its demise.
引力变得极度集中  将一切都吞噬
Their gravity gets so concentrated, it swallows everything.
一切  甚至是光
Everything, even light.
-这真的会发生吗  -数学说可以
- Can that really happen? - The math says it can.
如果我们能发表论文
If we can get published,
也许有天  天文学家就能找到一例
then perhaps one day an astronomer finds one.
但目前  我只有理论
But right now, all I have is theory,
无法影响人们的生活
which can't impact people's lives.
如果你要往西班牙汇款
Well, if you're going to send money to Spain,
可以通过共产党
do it through the Communist Party.
他们可以把钱送到前线
They can get it to the front lines.
玛丽让我拿这些过来
Mary sent me with these.
-我叫吉恩  -罗伯特
- I'm Jean. - Robert.
哈康·薛瓦利埃
Haakon Chevalier.
上个月在希尔博家的工会会议上见过
That union meeting at Serber's last month.
没错  没错
Right, right, yes.
谢谢
Oh, thank you.
罗伯特说他不是共产党
Robert here says he's not a communist.
说明他还不够了解共产党
Well, then he doesn't know enough about it.
我读过《资本论》  全部三卷
Oh, I've read Das Kapital, all three volumes.
这算吗
Does that count?
这说明你比大多数党员更博览群书
It would make you better-read than most party members.
挺晦涩的  有一个观点...
Turgid stuff. There's some thinking, um...
"所有权就是偷窃"
"Ownership is theft."
-财产  -财产
- Property. - Property?
是财产  不是所有权
Property, not ownership.
不好意思  我读的是德语原文
I'm sorry, I read it in the original German.
书不重要  重要的是想法
It's not about the book. It's about the ideas.
你听起来并不笃定
And you sound uncommitted.
我笃定的是自由思考如何让我们的世界更好
I'm committed to thinking freely about how to improve our world.
为什么要把自己局限于一个教条呢
Why limit yourself to one dogma?
你是物理学家  你会对规律挑挑拣拣吗
You're a physicist. Do you pick and choose rules?
还是利用规律  引导能量  取得进步
Or do you use the discipline to channel your energies into progress?
我喜欢有一点回旋空间
I like a little wiggle room.
你总是遵守党的路线吗
Do you always toe the party line?
我也喜欢回旋空间
I like my wiggle room, too.
怎么了
What?
等等  等等
Wait, wait, wait.
没想到啊
Unexpected.
什么
What?
你不是物理学家吗
For a physicist.
你只有一架子弗洛伊德的书吗
You only have a shelf full of Freud?
-实际上  我更偏向...  -荣格学派
- Well, actually, my background's more... - Jungian?
你知道分析心理学
You know analysis?
我在剑桥读研究生的时候
When I was in post-grad at Cambridge,
我遇到了一些小麻烦
I had a little trouble.
-是嘛  -我试图毒害我的导师
- I'll bite. - I tried to poison my tutor.
-你恨他吗  -我非常喜欢他
- Did you hate him? - I liked him very much.
你只是需要跟人上床
You just needed to get laid.
我的心理医生们花了两年时间
It took my analysts two years,
可能都没有如此一针见血
and I don't think they ever put it that succinctly.
你让所有人相信
You have everyone convinced
你是个"复杂"的人
you're more complicated than you actually are.
我们都是简单的人  我猜
We're all simple souls, I guess.
我不是
I'm not.
这是什么
What's this?
梵语
Sanskrit.
你读得懂
You can read this?
我在学
I'm learning.
读读看
Read this.
在这一部分
Well, in this part,
-毗湿奴展现了他多臂的自我...  -不
- Vishnu reveals his multi-armed self... - No.
读原文
Read the words.
"如今  我已成为死神"
"And now I am become Death...
"世界的毁灭者"
"destroyer of worlds."
这里就行
This'll do.
黎明前风会停的
It'll break before dawn.
夜间气温下降
Air cools overnight.
就在天亮之前  风会停下来
Just before dawn, it breaks.
我要结婚了
Well, so, I'm getting married.
-弗兰克  恭喜你  -谢谢  谢谢
- Frank! Congratulations! - Thank you, thank you.
-和杰姬吗  -是的  杰姬
- To Jackie? - Yeah, to Jackie.
那个服务员
The waitress?
奥比  被你说中了  风变小了
Oppie, you're right. It's letting up.
我出去看看有没有星星
I'm gonna go see if there's any stars.
你总说普通民众怎样怎样
All your talk about the common man,
但你还是看不上杰姬  是不是
but Jackie's not good enough for you, hmm?
听说我们入党  你的失望藏都藏不住
We joined the party, and you can't hide your disappointment.
为什么  因为你才有资格做这种大事是吗
Why? Is that because that's supposed to be your thing?
我还没有入党  弗兰克
I haven't joined the party, Frank.
我认为她也不应该劝你入党
And I don't think she should have convinced you to either.
-系里教职工一半都是党员  -没那么多
- Half of the faculty is communist. - Not that half.
我是你哥哥  弗兰克  我想让你谨慎点
I'm your brother, Frank, and I want you to be cautious.
我还想拧断你的脖子呢
And I want to wring your neck.
我不想一辈子都过得谨小慎微
I won't live my life afraid to make a mistake.
你幸福  我就幸福
You're happy... I'm happy.
你能为我而幸福  我就幸福
So then I'm happy you're happy that I'm happy.
我甚至觉得能看到暗星  就是你研究的那种
I feel like I can see one of those dark stars that you're working on.
看不到的
You can't.
所以才叫"暗"星  它们的引力能吞噬光线
That's the whole point. Their gravity swallows light.
就像宇宙中的一个洞
It's like a kind of hole in space.
弗兰克还好吗
Is Frank okay?
好  只不过他哥太差劲了
Yes. He just has a shitty brother.
这里确实特别
It is special here.
我小时候
When I was a kid...
就想  要是我能找到办法
I thought if I could find a way...
将物理和新墨西哥州结合起来
to combine physics and New Mexico,
我的人生就完美了
my life would be perfect.
-说这话还为时过早  -是啊
- Little remote for that. - Yes.
去睡一会儿吧
Let's get some sleep.
我们今天看到的那座平顶山
That mesa we saw today,
是我在这世上最喜欢的地方之一
one of my favorite places in the world.
-明天我们去爬  -那山叫什么名字
- Tomorrow we'll climb it. - What's it called?
洛斯阿拉莫斯
Los Alamos.
我今天没想到要见你
I didn't expect to see you today.
我还得先预约吗
Do I have to make an appointment?
阿尔瓦雷茨
Alvarez?
奥比  奥比
Oppie! Oppie!
什么  怎么了
What? What is it?
他们成功了
They've done it.
他们成功了  德国的哈恩和斯特拉斯曼
They've done it. Hahn and Strassmann in Germany.
他们让铀核裂变了
They split the uranium nucleus.
怎么做到的
How?
用中子轰击铀核
Bombard it with neutrons.
这是核裂变
It's a nuclear fission.
他们做到了  他们分裂了原子
They did it. They split the atom.
这不可能
That's not possible.
我去尝试复制实验
I'm gonna try to reproduce it.
看到没  不可能做到
See? Can't be done.
方法优雅
Very elegant.
过程清楚
Quite clear.
只是有一个问题
There's just one problem.
哪里
Where?
隔壁
Next door.
阿尔瓦雷茨成功了
Alvarez did it.
看
And look.
这些裂变脉冲  非常强烈
These fission pulses, they're massive.
过去十分钟里我看到了三十次
I've seen 30 of these in the past ten minutes.
理论是有局限的
Theory will take you only so far.
在这一过程中
During the process...
裂变释放出的中子能量极高
extra neutrons boil off,
可以再去分裂其他的铀原子核
which could be used to split other uranium atoms.
链式反应
Chain reaction.
你跟我想的一样吗
You're thinking what I'm thinking.
不止你我  世上所有看到这篇报道的物理学家
You, me, and every other physicist around the world
都会这么想
who's seen the news.
我怎么不...你们在说什么
I just... what, what are we all thinking?
炸弹  阿尔瓦雷茨
A bomb, Alvarez.
做炸弹
A bomb.
我告诉过你  罗伯特  别他妈再送花了
I told you, Robert, no more fucking flowers.
我不懂  你到底要我怎样
I don't understand what you want from me.
我什么也不要
I don't want anything from you!
-说是这么说  却又打电话找我  -你别接啊
- Well, you say that, and then you call. - Well, don't answer.
你打来我一定会接的
I'll always answer.
行吧
Fine.
别再送花就行了
Just no more flowers.
你不来吗
You're not coming?
要知难而退啊  罗伯特
You have to know when you're beaten, Robert.
没那么简单  哈康
It's not that simple, Haak.
薛瓦利埃  你好  芭芭拉  你好
Chevalier, good to see you. It's O...Barbara, good to see you.
还有声名远扬的奥本海默博士
And the illustrious Dr. Oppenheimer.
-我是埃尔滕顿  -幸会
- I'm Eltenton. - Oh, pleasure.
请进
Please, please.
大学里成立劳工组织的事  你来讲两句吧
Why don't you say a word about organized labor on campuses?
好吗  请让一让  让一让
Yes? Coming through, coming through!
我在壳牌工作
I work at Shell.
化学家和工程师都加入了组织
We've signed up chemists, we've signed up engineers.
科学界和学术界人士也一起吧
So why not sciences and academia?
奥比  奥比  奥比  奥比
Oppie! Oppie! Oppie! Oppie!
讲师都加入了
Teachers are unionized.
教授为什么不呢
Why not professors?
你不是还有事吗
Don't you have somewhere to be?
劳伦斯  科研人士也有权利
Lawrence, academics have rights too.
我不是说那个  我有个组会要开
Look, it's not that. I've got a group coming.
-那我旁听  -这次不行
- I'll sit in. - Not this one.
理查德  布什博士
Richard, Dr. Bush.
二位怎么北上来这里了
What brings you two up north?
理查德  你转告露丝  我周四去帕萨迪纳
Richard, you tell Ruth I'll be down in Pasadena Thursday.
黑洞的文章  中了
Paper on black holes, it's in!
哈特兰在哪儿
Where's Hartland?
找一下哈特兰  去找他
Get Hartland. Get Hartland.
1939年9月1日  世界会铭记这一天
September 1st, 1939? The world's gonna remember this day.
哈特兰  我们的论文刊印出来了
Oh, Hartland, our paper, it's in print.
有人抢了你的风头
You've been upstaged.
在不列颠战役期间  我发现
During the Battle of Britain, I found myself
自己越来越难以认同
increasingly out of sympathy with the...
共产党人主张的中立政策
policy of neutrality that communists advocated.
但希特勒入侵苏联后  我们与苏联成了盟友
But after Hitler invaded Russia and we became allies,
你对共产党人的认同有没有回升
these communist sympathies, do they return?
没有
No.
我得声明一下
I need to make clear that
我改变了对苏联的看法
my changing views on Russia did not mean
并不意味着我会与其他持不同观点的人绝交
a sharp break from those who held different views.
我妻子吉蒂在之前的一段婚姻中
For a year or two during a previous marriage,
当过一两年共产党员
my wife Kitty had been a Communist Party member.
我把好东西都藏在这里
This is where I keep the good stuff.
这里不是托尔曼夫妇家吗
Well, I thought this was the Tolmans' house.
我在加州理工的时候就住他们家
I live with them while I'm at Caltech.
你俩需要我帮忙吗
Do you two need anything?
不用  露丝
We're good, Ruthie.
话说  你是一名生物学家
So, you're a biologist.
但我毕业之后就当了家庭主妇
Well, somehow I have graduated to housewife.
你能给我讲讲量子力学吗
Can you explain quantum mechanics to me?
-听起来挺玄乎的  -确实
- Seems baffling. - Yes, it is.
这个杯子
Well, this glass,
杯中的酒  这个台面
this drink... this countertop...
还有我们的身体
Our bodies.
一切的一切
All of it.
几乎都是空的
It's mostly empty space.
是束缚在一起的一组组微小能量波
Groupings of tiny energy waves bound together.
被什么束缚
By what?
足够强的吸引力
Forces of attraction strong enough
强到能让我们认为物质是固体
to convince us that matter is solid.
让我的身体不会穿过你的身体
Stop my body passing through yours.
你跟哈里森博士是夫妻
You're married to Dr. Harrison.
聚少离多
Not very.
有一个人  我对她...
There is someone that I feel...
她对你也是一样吗
Does she feel that way?
有时吧
Sometimes.
不够多
Not enough.
我要去新墨西哥州了
You know, I'm going to New Mexico.
去我的牧场  跟朋友们一起
To my ranch, with friends.
你也来吧
You should come.
我是说  和你丈夫一起
I meant, with your husband.
是啊
Yes, you did.
你明知道加不加这句话  结果都一样
Because you know it won't make a bit of difference.
你为什么嫁给他
Why did you marry him?
我那时很迷茫  他很温柔
I was lost, and... he was kind.
迷茫
Lost?
我上一任丈夫去世了
Well, my previous husband had died, and...
28岁的我毫无准备就当了寡妇
at 28, I wasn't really ready to be a widow.
-你第一任丈夫是谁  -无名小卒
- Who was your first husband? - Nobody.
我第二任丈夫是乔·达莱特
My second husband was Joe Dallet.
他跟我一样也出身富裕
He was from money, like me,
但他当时是俄亥俄州扬斯敦的工会组织者
but he was a union organizer in Youngstown, Ohio.
我爱得疯狂
I fell hard.
-有多疯狂  -在接下来的四年里
- How hard? - Hard enough to spend the next four years
甘愿仅靠豆子和煎饼果腹
living off beans and pancakes,
在工厂门口发《每日工人》的那种疯狂
handing out the Daily Worker at factory gates.
到1936年  我对乔说  我再也受不了了
By '36, I just told Joe I couldn't take it anymore.
我退了党
Quit the party.
一年之后  我又想跟他复合
A year later, I wanted him back.
只要他  不要《每日工人》  然后...
Him, not the Daily Worker. And...
他说  "好啊  我们去西班牙的路上见"
he said: "Swell, I'll meet you on my way to Spain."
去为忠诚派而战吗
Went to fight for the Loyalists?
然后他去参军了  我等啊等
And then he went to the brigades and I waited.
然后
And...
他上战场后
Joe got himself killed
第一次从战壕探头就丢了命
first time he popped his head out of the trench.
意识形态害死了乔  毫无意义
Ideology got Joe killed, for nothing.
西班牙共和国可不是毫无意义
The Spanish Republic isn't nothing.
我丈夫赔上我们两人的未来
My husband offered both our futures
换来一颗本该射进泥滩的法西斯子弹击中他自己
to stop one fascist bullet from embedding itself in a mud bank.
这就是毫无意义
That's the definition of nothing.
-有点过于简化了  -是务实
- Seems a little reductive. - Pragmatic.
结果我就落得这个境地了
Now here I am.
管它现在是什么情况
Wherever the hell this is.
我不希望你从别人口中听说
I didn't want you to hear it from anyone else.
至少这次你没再送我花
At least you didn't bring me flowers.
我们心里都清楚  你想要的不是我  吉恩
We both know I'm not what you want, Jean.
对  可是以后我俩再也没可能了
Yeah, but it's a door closing.
不
No.
至少我不这么认为
Not as far as I'm concerned, no.
你这就让她怀上了  动作够快
You knocked her up. Fast work.
好男人是很抢手
Can't keep a good man down.
我是说她
I meant her.
她知道她想要什么
She knew what she wanted.
她丈夫怎么办
What about the husband?
我们聊过了
We talked.
他们打算离婚
They're getting a divorce,
这样我俩就能赶在她显怀之前结婚
so we can get married before she starts showing.
真体面啊
How civilized.
你个傻子
You idiot.
这是你们科学家的圈子
This is your community.
你以为天才就能藐视规律了吗
You think the rules don't apply to the golden boy?
才华确实能掩盖不少问题
Brilliance makes up for a lot.
这世上懂你的人不多
Don't alienate the only people in the world
别疏远他们
that understand what you do.
没准哪天你会需要他们
One day you might need them.
FAECT
F-a-e-c-t!
建筑师  工程师  化学家与技师联盟
Federation of Architects, Engineers, Chemists and Technicians.
洛马尼茨  他们一个月付你多少钱
Lomanitz, what do you get paid a month?
重点不是这个  劳伦斯
That's not the point, Lawrence.
你们跟农民和码头工人
What do any of you have in common
有什么共同点吗
with farm laborers and dock workers?
有很多
Plenty.
都出去  快
Everybody out. Now!
你留下
Not you.
你在干什么
What are you doing?
工会而已
It's a trade union.
满是共党的工会
Filled with communists.
那又怎样  我又没入党
So? I haven't joined the party.
正是因为这破事
They won't let me bring you onto the project
他们不让我带你参加那个项目
because of this shit.
连项目是干什么的都不让我告诉你
They won't even let me tell you what the project is.
我知道是什么项目
Oh, I know what the project is.
是吗
Oh, really?
我们都听说了
We've all heard
爱因斯坦和西拉德给罗斯福写信
about Einstein and Szilard's letter to Roosevelt
提醒他德国人可能造出炸弹
warning him the Germans could make a bomb,
我清楚纳粹有了炸弹就意味着什么
and I know what it means for the Nazis to have a bomb.
难道我不清楚吗
And I don't?
被他们赶进集中营的  不是你的同胞
It's not your people they're herding into camps.
是我的
It's mine.
你以为是我告诉了他们你的政治立场吗
You think that I tell them about your politics?
下次你从集会回家的时候
The next time you're coming home from a meeting,
从后视镜里看一眼
why don't you take a look in the rearview mirror,
注意电话听筒的杂音
listen to the sounds on your phone line,
别再这么天真了好吗
and stop being so goddamn naive?
他们为什么会关心我做什么
Why would they care what I do?
因为你不只是自命不凡
Because you're not just self-important,
你是真的很重要
you're actually important.
好吧
Okay.
我明白了
I get it.
你要是能再...
If you could just be a little more...
务实一点  我会和洛马尼茨他们谈谈的
Pragmatic. I'll talk to Lomanitz, I'll talk to the others.
不用担心  我能解决好
You don't have to worry, it's done.
劳伦斯
Lawrence.
那欢迎加入战争
Then welcome to the war.
我填写了第一份安全调查表
I filled out my first security questionnaire
并被告知  我与左翼团体的联系
and was informed that my involvement with left-wing groups
不会妨碍我为核项目工作
would not prove a bar to my working on the atomic program.
为什么他与共产党人的关系
Why were his communist associations
在战争期间没被视为安全风险
not seen as a security risk during the war?
参议员先生  我不可能
Senator, I can't possibly answer for security clearance
为在我认识此人几年前就获批的安全许可负责
granted years before I ever met the man.
好吧  那之后呢
Fine. What about after?
战后
After the war,
奥本海默博士
Dr. Oppenheimer
是世上最受敬重的科学家
was the most respected scientific voice in the world.
因此我才请他来执掌高等研究院
That's why I asked him to run the Institute.
因此他为原子能委员会出谋划策
That's why he advised the Atomic Energy Commission.
就这么简单
Simple as that.
他们指控我什么
What are they accusing me of?
我觉得他们只是想知道
I think they just want to know
1947到1954年间
what happened between 1947 and 1954
是什么让你改变了对奥本海默安全许可的决定
to change your mind on Oppenheimer's security clearance.
不是我
I didn't.
我是原子能委员会的主席
I was chair of the AEC, but it wasn't me
-但对罗伯特的指控不是我提的  -那是谁
- that brought the charges against Robert. - Who did?
某个国会原子能联合委员会的前成员
Some former staff member of the Joint Congressional Committee.
他叫波登  是个激进的反共分子
He was a rabid anti-communist named Borden.
他写信给联调局  要求他们采取行动
He wrote to the FBI demanding they take action.
联调局  为什么不直接找原子能委员会
The FBI? Why not go to the AEC direct?
太过直接  大家就会知道你是主使
You'd get caught holding the knife yourself.
波登为什么和奥本海默过不去
What did Borden have against Oppenheimer?
这是麦卡锡时代
This is the McCarthy era.
跟赤色沾一点边就会失业
People hounded out of jobs for any hint of red, and...
从奥本海默的安全档案可知
Reading Oppenheimer's security file,
他的共产党弟弟
his communist brother,
弟媳  未婚妻  好友  妻子
sister-in-law, fiancée, best friend, wife.
更不用说薛瓦利埃事件了
That's before we even get to the Chevalier incident.
但波登是怎么拿到奥本海默的安全档案的
But how would Borden have access to Oppenheimer's security file?
有人给他的
Because somebody gave it to him.
某个想让罗伯特闭嘴的人
Somebody who wanted Robert silenced.
-谁  -谁知道呢
- Who? - Who knows?
罗伯特没照顾到
Robert didn't take care
华盛顿那些政治掮客的想法
not to upset the power brokers in Washington.
他对原子能的看法坚定不移
His opinions on the atom became definitive,
对我们这些凡人也不常有耐心
and he wasn't always patient with us mere mortals.
我就遭受过不少苛刻的对待
I came in for plenty of harsh treatment.
之前有次原子能委员会
There was an AEC vote
投票表决同位素到挪威的出口
on the export of isotopes to Norway,
他们拉上罗伯特  让我出尽洋相
and they drafted in Robert to make me look like a fool.
不过奥本海默博士
But Dr. Oppenheimer,
我们已听施特劳斯上将说
we've already heard from Admiral Strauss
我们的敌人可能会利用这些同位素
that these isotopes could be useful to our enemies
制造核武器
in the production of atomic weapons.
议员先生  造核武器还可能用到铲子呢
Congressman, you could use a shovel in making atomic weapons.
的确会用到
In fact, you do.
造核武器还可能用到一瓶啤酒
You could use a bottle of beer in making atomic weapons.
的确会用到
In fact, you do.
要我说同位素还没有电子元件有用
I'd say isotopes are less useful than electronic components,
但比三明治有用
but more useful than a sandwich.
天才不一定有智慧
Genius is no guarantee of wisdom.
这人为何洞悉一切却又如此盲目
How could this man who saw so much be so blind?
吉蒂
Kitty?
Kitty.
那个项目
The project.
我加入了
I'm in.
-我加入了  -来庆祝吧
- I'm in! - Let's celebrate.
你不该去哄哄他吗
Shouldn't you go to him?
我他妈哄了他一天了
I have been going to him all fucking day.
我不知道该如何开口
I don't know how to say this.
我羞于启齿
I'm ashamed to ask.
说吧
Anything.
-拜托照顾彼得  -没问题
- Take Peter. - Sure.
不  是照顾一阵子  哈康
No, for a while, Haak.
一阵子
A while.
-吉蒂知道你来这里了吗  -她当然知道
- Does Kitty know you're here? - Yes, of course she knows.
她当然知道
Of course she knows.
我们太差劲了  自私  差劲
We're awful people. Selfish, awful people.
算了当我没问
Forget I asked.
自私  差劲的人
Selfish, awful people,
是意识不到他们的自私和差劲的
they don't know they're selfish and awful.
坐吧
Sit, sit, sit.
罗伯特  你能看到现实世界以外的另一个世界
Robert, you see beyond the world we live in.
是要付出代价的
There is a price to be paid for that.
我们当然会帮你
Of course we'll help you.
一切都在改变  罗伯特
Everything's changing, Robert.
有了孩子自然会改变...
Having a child was always going to change...
不  世界在转向新的方向
No, the world is pivoting in some new direction.
在改革
Reforming.
这是你的机会
This is your moment.
我们在召集人马  研究...
We're putting together a group to study...
不是"我们"
We shouldn't be doing anything.
是"你"
You should.
劳伦斯搞不定的
Lawrence won't get this done.
托尔曼和拉比也不能  你可以
Or Tolman or Rabi. You will.
那些穿军装的是什么人
Who are the uniforms?
我还以为你知道呢
I thought you might know.
奥本海默博士
Dr. Oppenheimer.
我是格罗夫斯上校  这位是尼科斯中校
I'm Colonel Groves. This is Lieutenant Colonel Nichols.
送去干洗
Have that dry cleaned.
如果你这么对待一位中校的话
Well, if that's how you treat a lieutenant colonel,
我不敢想你会怎样对一名小小的物理学家
I'd hate to see how you treat a... humble physicist.
等我以后遇到了你就知道了
If I ever meet one, I'll let you know.
全世界都在打仗
Theaters of combat all over the world,
我却只能留在华盛顿
but I have to stay in Washington.
-为什么  -我建了五角大楼
- Why? - I built the Pentagon.
要员们很喜欢
The brass likes it so much,
于是又让我掌管曼哈顿工程区
they made me take over the Manhattan Engineer District.
-那是什么  -别装了
- Which is? - Don't be a smartass.
你清楚得很
You know damn well what it is.
你和全国物理系半数教职员工都清楚
You and half of every physics department across the country.
这是首要问题
That's problem number one.
我还以为搞到足够多的铀矿石
I thought problem number one
才是首要问题
would be securing enough uranium ore.
-一千两百吨  我上任那天就买下了  -那加工呢
- 1,200 tons, bought the day I took charge. - Processing?
刚在田纳西州的橡树岭动工
Just broke ground at Oak Ridge, Tennessee.
现在我在物色项目负责人
Now I'm looking for a project director.
想到我了
And my name came up?
不是
Nope.
虽然你把量子物理学带到了美国
Even though you brought quantum physics to America,
让我还挺好奇的
which made me curious.
你调查出什么了
What have you found out?
你是个半吊子  花花公子  疑似共产党
You're a dilettante, a womanizer, a suspected communist.
我是支持新政的民主党
I'm a New Deal Democrat.
我说了是"疑似"
I said "suspected".
情绪多变  做作  高傲  神经质
Unstable, theatrical, egotistical, neurotic.
没找到优点  是吧
Nothing good, no?
甚至没句  "他很聪明  但是"
Not even "he's brilliant, but..."
聪明是你们这个圈子最基本的品质  所以没有
Well, brilliance is taken for granted in your circle, so no.
唯一一个夸了你的是
No, the only person who had anything good to say
理查德·托尔曼
was Richard Tolman.
托尔曼觉得你为人正直
Tolman thinks you have integrity,
但我还是觉得
but he also strikes me as a guy
他看人的本事不如科研
who knows more about science than people.
但你还是来了
Yet here you are.
你不太信任人
You don't take much on trust.
我什么都不信任
I don't take anything on trust.
你怎么没得诺贝尔奖
Why don't you have a Nobel Prize?
你怎么没当上将军
Why aren't you a general?
这事要是成了就当上了
They're making me one for this.
说不定我也一样
Perhaps I'll have the same luck.
造炸弹能得诺贝尔奖
The Nobel Prize for making a bomb?
阿尔弗雷德·诺贝尔发明了硝酸甘油炸药
Alfred Nobel invented dynamite.
你打算怎么做
So how would you proceed?
你说的是
You're talking about
抢在纳粹之前
turning theory into a practical weapon system
把理论变成可用的武器
faster than the Nazis.
他们已经比我们提前了12个月
Who have a 12-month head start.
-是18个月  -你怎么知道
- 18. - How could you possibly know that?
我们的快中子研究花了六个月
Our fast neutron research took six months.
纳粹指派的研究负责人
The man they've undoubtedly put in charge
肯定不会卡在这上面
will have made that leap instantly.
你觉得他们派谁负责了
Who do you think they put in charge?
维尔纳·海森堡
Werner Heisenberg.
他是我见过对原子结构
He has the most intuitive understanding of atomic structure
有着最直观认识的人
I have ever seen.
-你了解他的研究吗  -我了解他这个人
- You know his work? - I know him,
就像我了解瓦尔特·博特  冯·魏茨泽克  迪布纳
just like I know Walther Bothe, von Weizsäcker, Diebner.
硬碰硬比速度的话  德国人必胜
In a straight race, the Germans win.
-我们有一线希望  -是什么
- We've got one hope. - Which is?
反犹太主义
Antisemitism.
什么
What?
希特勒说量子物理学是"犹太人的科学"
Hitler called quantum physics "Jewish science".
跟爱因斯坦当面说的
Said it right to Einstein's face.
我们唯一的希望就是希特勒被仇恨蒙蔽
Our one hope is that Hitler is so blinded by hate
拒绝给海森堡提供足够的资源
that he's denied Heisenberg proper resources,
因为那将耗费海量资源
because it'll take vast resources.
而我国最优秀的科学家齐心协力
Our nation's best scientists working together.
但现在  大家散落在各地
Right now, they're scattered.
正好做到了权限分隔
Which gives us compartmentalization.
只有让所有人都清楚情况  才能高效工作
All minds have to see the whole task to contribute efficiently.
安全保密问题可能会让我们落后
Poor security may cost us the race.
但低效一定会
Inefficiency will.
反正德国人比我们知道得更多
The Germans know more than us anyway.
苏联人可不一定
The Russians don't.
慢着  我们在和谁打仗
Remind me, who are we at war with?
鉴于你的过去
Somebody with your past
你肯定不想让人觉得你忽视了保密工作
doesn't want to be seen downplaying the importance of security
没提防我们的共产党盟友
from our communist allies.
有道理  但是  不
Point taken, but... no.
你不能跟我说不
You don't get to say no to me.
我的职责就是在你搞错时跟你说不
It's my job to say no to you when you're wrong.
所以你接下这份工作了
So you have the job now?
我再想想
I'm considering it.
我明白你的名声从何而来了
I'm starting to see where you got your reputation.
我最喜欢的回应是
My favorite response:
"奥本海默连汉堡摊都管不好"
"Oppenheimer couldn't run a hamburger stand."
我是不行
I couldn't.
但我能管好曼哈顿计划
But I can run the Manhattan Project.
有一个办法保持平衡
There's a way to balance these things.
让劳伦斯继续管理伯克利这里的放射性实验室
Keep the Rad Lab here at Berkeley, under Lawrence.
西拉德管理芝加哥大学的冶金实验室
Met Lab in Chicago, under Szilard.
大规模精炼  你说在哪来着  田纳西州
Large-scale refining, where did you say, Tennessee?
-还有汉福德  -还有汉福德
- And Hanford. - And Hanford.
全美工业相关的科技创新
All America's industrial-minded scientific innovation,
都由铁路连接贯通  朝着一个目标
connected by rail, focused on one goal,
在时间和空间上都汇于一点
one point in space and time.
汇于这里  一个秘密实验室
And it comes together here, a secret laboratory.
在荒无人烟的地方  安全  自给自足
In the middle of nowhere, secure, self-sufficient.
设备  住房  施工
Equipment, housing, the works.
封闭式作业
Keep everyone there until it's done.
-我们需要学校  商店  教堂  -为什么
- We'll need a school, stores, a church. - Why?
如果不允许科学家带家属
If we don't let scientists bring their families,
那他们就没法全情投入
we'll never get the best.
你想要密不透风  就建座镇吧  要快
You want security, build a town. Build it fast.
在哪儿
Where?
欢迎来到洛斯阿拉莫斯
Welcome to Los Alamos.
那边有所男校  我们得征用它
There's a boys' school we'll have to commandeer,
本地的印第安人会来办葬礼
and the local Indians come up here for burial rites,
除此之外  荒无人烟
but apart from that, nothing.
方圆65千米皆是如此
40 miles. Any direction.
这就是我们的最佳地点
We'll have to find the perfect spot.
-为了什么  -为了成功
- For? - Success.
给他建个镇子  要快
Build him a town. Fast.
我们去招募科学家吧
Let's go recruit some scientists.
我为什么要抛家弃子
Why would I leave my family?
我说了  可以把家人带上
I told you, you can bring your family.
-我不是军人  奥比  -军人
- I'm not a soldier, Oppie. - A soldier?
他是将军  除了他我不需要其他军人了
He's a general. I've got all the soldier I need.
我能说到什么程度
What can I tell them?
海森堡  迪布纳  博特  玻尔
Heisenberg, Diebner, Bothe and Bohr.
这些人有什么共通之处
What do these men have in common?
-都是原子理论最杰出的科学家  -还有呢
- Uh, the greatest minds on atomic theory. - Yes, and?
你看着办吧
As much as you like.
说太多我自然会踹你的蛋
Until you feel my boot on your balls.
你懂同位素  你懂爆炸
You know isotopes, and you know explosives
你们是全球最顶尖的专家
better than anyone in the world.
但你不说你要干什么
But you can't tell us what you're doing.
-我不知道  -他们在纳粹那里
- I don't know. - The Nazis have them.
尼尔斯·玻尔在哥本哈根
Niels Bohr's in Copenhagen.
那也是纳粹的占领区
Under Nazi occupation.
普林斯顿不印报纸了吗
Did they stop printing newspapers in Princeton?
我们为什么要跑到个不毛之地
Why would we go to the middle of nowhere
还不知道要待多久
for who knows how long?
一两年吧  或者三年
For a year or two. Or three.
将军  能让我们单独聊聊吗
General, could you... give us a moment?
是要释放一种巨大的力量
It's about unleashing a strong force.
要赶在纳粹前面
Before the Nazis do.
天啊
Oh my god.
尼尔斯才不会为纳粹卖命
Niels won't work for the Nazis.
当然不会
No, never.
但他在纳粹地盘上  不在我们这
But while they have him, we don't.
所以我需要你
That's why I need you.
你凭什么觉得我会同意
Why would you think I'd do that?
凭什么  凭什么
Why? Why?
就凭这是史无前例的
How about because this is the most important fucking thing
重要事件
to ever happen in the history of the world?
够不够
How about that?
妈的
Fuck.
他们不会同意我参与的
They're not gonna let me onto this project.
哪怕战争结束了
And failing a security check
没通过安全审查也会影响我的职业
is not going to be good for a career even after the war.
所以你只能跟我们共事一段时间  那又如何
So you're a fellow traveler. So what?
现在国家进入紧急状态
This is a national emergency.
关于我也有些传言  但他们让我总负责
I've got some skeletons. They put me in charge.
他们需要我们
They need us.
总有一天就不需要了
Until they don't.
有可能把玻尔从丹麦带出来吗
Is there any chance of getting Bohr out of Denmark?
没门儿  我和英国那边联系过了
Yeah, no dice. I checked with the British.
除非盟军打回欧洲大陆
Until we get Allied boots back onto the continent,
不然没可能
there's just no way.
他就那么重要吗
Is he that important?
有几个人能证明爱因斯坦错了
How many people do you know who proved Einstein wrong?
飞机不是要快很多吗
You know, it really would be quicker to take a plane.
乘飞机太冒险了
A plane's too risky.
国家需要我们
The country needs us.
怎么了  伙计们
What happened, guys?
他们说那房子装不下粒子回旋加速器
They say the building's too small for this cyclotron.
让他们和建筑师开个会
Get them together with the architects.
这儿什么时候开始运行
When's this place supposed to open?
两个月后
Two months.
罗伯特  你是个即兴创作家  但...
Robert, you're the great improviser, but this...
你不能只想当然
you can't do in your head.
四个部门
Four divisions.
实验部  理论部  冶炼部
Experimental, theoretical, metallurgical.
谁负责理论部
Who's running theoretical?
我
I am.
这正是我担心的  你要管的太多了
That's what I was afraid of. You're spread too thin.
那你负责理论部
So you take theoretical.
我不准备来  罗伯特
I'm not coming here, Robert.
为什么
Why not?
炸弹爆炸  正义之人邪恶之人都将丧命
You drop a bomb and it falls on the just and the unjust.
我不希望三个世纪的物理学巅峰之作
I don't wish the culmination of three centuries of physics
是一件大规模杀伤性武器
to be a weapon of mass destruction.
伊西
Izzy...
我不知道我们是否有资格掌控这种武器
I don't know if we can be trusted with such a weapon.
但我知道纳粹一定不可以
But I know the Nazis can't.
我们别无选择
We have no choice.
那...
Then...
你要做的第二件事
the second thing you have to do
是让汉斯·贝特负责理论部
is appoint Hans Bethe to run the theoretical division.
等等  那第一件事是什么
Wait, what was the first?
脱了这身可笑的军服
Take off that ridiculous uniform.
你是科学家
You're a scientist.
格罗夫斯坚持让我们穿
Groves is insisting we join.
让格罗夫斯吃屎去吧
Tell Groves to go shit in his hat.
他们需要的是科学家
They need us for who we are.
所以做你自己就行
So be yourself.
还要更好
Only better.
这是唯一一把钥匙
This is the only key.
泰勒已经来了
And Teller's already here.
要我带他进来吗
Shall I just show him in?
不  等其他人都到了
No, let's wait for the others.
我们开始吧
Let's get started.
-你好  爱德华  -好
- Hello, Edward. - Yes.
先生们  洛斯阿拉莫斯的T区完工前
Gentlemen, so, we will work here
我们先在这里工作
until the T Section at Los Alamos is finished.
爱德华  能让我...
Edward, can I...?
这更重要
This is more important.
我计算链式反应时
When I calculated the chain reaction,
发现一种很令人不安的可能性
I found a rather troubling possibility.
这不可能
No, this can't be right.
告诉我你是怎么算的
Show me how you did your calculations.
好
Yes.
-指数级的  -不  不
- Exponential. - No, no, no. No.
这不可能是真的
This is fantasy.
泰勒的计算不可能是对的
Teller's calculations can't be right.
我去趟普林斯顿  你也自己算一遍
Do them yourself while I go to Princeton.
-去做什么  -去找爱因斯坦
- What for? - To talk to Einstein.
但你俩对很多事情都有分歧
Well, there's not much common ground between you two.
所以我要看看他的观点
That's why I should get his view.
阿尔伯特
Albert.
奥本海默博士
Ah, Dr. Oppenheimer.
你认识哥德尔博士吗
Have you met Dr. Gödel?
我们经常在这儿散步
We walk here most days.
树木的结构最具启发性了
Trees have the most inspiring structures.
阿尔伯特  能和你单独聊聊吗
Albert, might I have a word?
当然  失陪一下  库尔特
Of course. Excuse me, Kurt.
库尔特曾绝食过一段日子
Some days Kurt refuses to eat.
即使在普林斯顿
Even in Princeton,
他还觉得纳粹会给他下毒
he's convinced that the Nazis can poison his food.
这...  这是谁算的
Whose, whose work is this?
泰勒
Teller's.
你怎么看
What do you take it to mean?
中子撞进原子核
Neutrons smash into the nucleus,
释放出的中子又撞进其他原子核
releasing neutrons to smash into other nuclei.
到达临界点
Criticality.
不可逆转  巨大的爆炸力
Point of no return. Massive explosive force.
但这一次  链式反应没有停止
But this time, the chain reaction doesn't stop.
这将点燃大气层
It would ignite the atmosphere.
引爆核装置
When we detonate an atomic device,
可能引发的链式反应  将...
we might start a chain reaction that...
毁灭世界
destroys the world.
所以你来找我
So here we are, hmm?
你在概率的量子世界中迷失了
Lost in your quantum world of probabilities,
需要确定性
and needing certainty.
你能亲自算一遍吗
Can you run the calculations yourself?
你我唯一的共同点
About the only thing you and I have in common
就是蔑视数学
is a disdain for mathematics.
伯克利谁在算这个
Who's working on this in Berkeley?
汉斯·贝特
Hans Bethe.
他会找出答案的
Well, he'll get to the truth.
如果答案是灾难呢
And if the truth is catastrophic?
那你就停手  并且将发现告诉纳粹
Then you stop, and you share your findings with the Nazis.
这样两边都不会毁灭世界
So neither side destroys the world.
罗伯特
Robert.
这是你的  不是我的
This is yours, not mine.
泰勒错了
Teller's wrong.
他错了
He's wrong.
知道了泰勒的关键性假设
When you know Teller's critical assumptions,
真相就显现了
the real picture emerges.
结论呢
Bottom line?
核反应失控的几率
The chances of an out-of-control nuclear reaction
几近于零
are near-zero.
"几近"于零
Near-zero.
奥比  这可是好消息啊
Oppie, this is good news.
能再算一遍吗
Can you run them again?
可答案是一样的
Oh, you'll get the same answer.
真正引爆之前
Until they actually detonate one of these things,
最大的确定性就是这个
the best assurance you're going to get is this.
几近于零
Near-zero.
理论是有局限的
Theory will take you only so far.
-好啊  -好
- Hello! - Hi.
我们好想他
We missed him.
要领养吗
You want to adopt?
她开玩笑的
She's kidding.
离开前我们想见见你们
We wanted to see you before we left.
要去一个神秘的地方了
For parts unknown.
知道前几天我碰见谁了吗
You know who I ran into the other day?
埃尔滕顿
Eltenton.
壳牌的化学家吗  工会那个人
That chemist from Shell? The union guy?
没错  FAECT那个人
Yeah, the FAECT guy.
他一直在抱怨  我们这仗打得不对劲
He was moaning about how we're handling the war.
怎么说
How so?
缺少和盟友们的合作
Lack of cooperation with our allies.
据说我们的政府
Apparently, our government's not sharing
没有和苏联人分享任何研究信息
any research with the Russians.
他说大部分科学家都觉得这项政策是愚蠢的
He said most scientists think the policy is stupid.
-是吗  -是的
- Oh, yeah? - Yeah.
他说如果有人想要绕过官方渠道
He mentioned that if anyone had anything they wanted to pass on,
传递什么信息  他可以帮忙
going around official channels, that he could help.
那是叛国
That would be treason.
当然
Yes, of course.
我只是觉得应该告诉你
I just thought you should know.
孩子睡下了
The brat is down.
马提尼酒呢
Where are the martinis?
马上来
Coming right up.
我们的谈话到此为止
The conversation ended there.
我们是老朋友了  我从没觉得
Nothing in our long-standing friendship would have led me to believe
薛瓦利埃是在套话
that Chevalier was actually seeking information,
而且我非常肯定  他对我当时的工作
and I am certain that he had no idea of the work
毫不知情
in which I was engaged.
长期以来我都知道
It has long been clear to me that
我当时应该立即上报这件事
I should have reported this incident at once.
奥本海默事件
The Oppheimer situation highlights the tension
凸显了科学家和国家安全机构之间的紧张关系
between scientists and the security apparatus.
为了了解候选人在原子能委员会任职期间
In hopes of learning how the nominee handled such issues
是如何处理此类问题的
during his time at the AEC,
我们会请一位科学家出席
we'll have a scientist appearing before the committee.
他们请的谁
Who are they bringing in?
还没有说
They hadn't said.
主席先生  我提名的是商务部长
Mr. Chairman, if I may, I'm nominated for Commerce Secretary.
为什么需要听取科学家的意见
Why seek the opinion of scientists?
事关内阁职位  上将
This is a cabinet post, Admiral.
我们需要广听各方面的声音
We seek a wide range of opinion.
我想知道这位作证的科学家是谁
I'd like to know the name of the scientist testifying.
希望有交叉询问的机会
I'd like the chance to cross-examine.
这里不是法庭
This is not a court.
这算哪门子走形式
Formality, huh?
自1925年以来还没有总统提名的内阁候选人落选
No presidential cabinet nominee has failed to be confirmed since 1925.
这只是游戏规则而已
This is just how the game is played.
职位肯定是你的了  路易斯  友好点
It's in the bag, Lewis. So play nice.
他们找来一个科学家  又能怎样
They bring in a scientist, so what?
我比你更了解科学家  顾问先生
You don't know scientists like I do, Counselor.
他们厌恶任何质疑他们判断的人
They resent anyone who questions their judgment,
你不是科学家的话更甚
especially if you're not one of them.
我做过原子能委员会主席
I was chair of the AEC.
罗伯特的遭遇  我是最好的出气筒
I'm easy to blame for what happened to Robert.
我们不能让参议院认为
We can't have the Senate thinking
您不受科学家们支持  先生
the scientific community doesn't support you, sir.
或者我们转换策略
Or should we pivot?
-什么样的策略  -欣然接受
- To what? - And embrace it.
"我与奥本海默开战  美国赢得胜利"
"I fought Oppenheimer, and the US won."
我认为不必走到那一步
I don't think we need to go there.
我们能不能找到一个了解内情的人
Isn't there someone we can call who knows what really happened?
-泰勒  -他会给他们留下好印象的
- Teller. - He'll make an impression.
能不能打听到出席科学家的身份
Can you get the name of the scientist they've called?
-也许吧  -挖出战时他身在芝加哥
- Probably. - Find out if he was based in Chicago
还是洛斯阿拉莫斯
or Los Alamos during the war.
这有什么关系
Why does that matter?
因为如果他在芝加哥
Well, if he was based in Chicago,
一定是在西拉德和费米手下工作
they worked under Szilard and Fermi,
而不是在洛斯阿拉莫斯跟奥比一条心
not the cult to Oppie in Los Alamos.
那个地方是罗伯特一手建立的
Robert built that damn place.
创始人  市长  警长都是他
He was founder, mayor, sheriff.
三位一体
All rolled into one.
再有一个酒馆就万事俱备了
Now all it needs is a saloon.
这里没有厨房
There's no kitchen.
真的吗  我会想办法的
Really? We'll fix that.
铁丝网  枪炮
Barbed wire? Guns?
-奥比  -我们在打仗呢  汉斯
- Oppie... - We're at war, Hans.
哈利法克斯
Halifax.
1917年
1917.
一艘满载弹药的货船在港口爆炸
A cargo ship carrying munitions explodes in the harbor.
一次巨大且突然的化学反应
A vast and sudden chemical reaction.
史上最大的人为爆炸
The biggest man-made explosion in history.
现在来算一算  如果换成核反应
Now, let's calculate how much more destructive it would have been
破坏力比化学反应大多少
if it were a nuclear and not a chemical reaction,
用吨TNT当量表示
expressing power in terms of tons of TNT.
但会有几千几万吨TNT当量
But it will be thousands.
那就换成千吨TNT当量
Well, then, kilotons.
如果用铀-235
Using U-235,
炸弹需要...
the bomb will need a...
抱歉  装置需要一个15千克的球体
Sorry. Gadget will need a 33-pound sphere
大约这么大
about this size,
如果用钚  需要一个4.5千克的球体
or using plutonium, a ten-pound sphere.
橡树岭上个月精炼出的铀一共有这么多
Here's the amount of uranium Oak Ridge refined all of last month.
汉福德生产的钚有这么多
And the Hanford plant made this much plutonium.
浓缩够量以后  还需要引爆的方法
Now, if we can enrich these amounts, we need a way to detonate them.
我们讲的让你无聊了吗  爱德华
Are we boring you, Edward?
确实有一点
A little bit, yes.
能问问为什么吗
May I ask why?
我们来之前  早就知道裂变炸弹是可行的
We all entered this room knowing a fission bomb was possible.
离开之前是不是应该创造点新东西
How about we leave it with something new?
比如
Such as?
不用铀和钚  改用氢
Instead of uranium or plutonium, we use hydrogen.
重氢  氘
Heavy hydrogen. Deuterium.
这样  我们用巨大的压力
You see, we compact the atoms together
把原子压缩到一起  引发聚变反应
under great pressure to induce a fusion reaction.
这样能量就不是千吨级  而是百万吨级
Then we'll get not kilotons, but megatons.
等一下  等一下
Okay, hang on, hang on.
那么如何产生足够的能量  让氢原子聚变呢
So how do you generate enough force to fuse hydrogen atoms?
用一个小型裂变炸弹
A small fission bomb.
还是嘛
There we are!
既然无论如何都要用到裂变炸弹
Well, since we're going to need one anyway,
能不能回到之前的讨论
can we get back to the business at hand?
同位素出口问题并不是
The isotopes issue wasn't your most important
你与奥本海默博士最大的政策分歧
policy disagreement with Dr. Oppenheimer.
最大的分歧在于氢弹  对吗
It was the hydrogen bomb, wasn't it?
我们是同事  对很多问题和而不同
As colleagues, we agreed to disagree on a great many things, uh...
其中一个就是需不需要开始研究氢弹  是的
And one of them was the need for an H-bomb program, yes.
通知得紧急  感谢各位前来
Thanks for convening on short notice.
难以置信
I can't believe it.
但事已至此  告诉我  我们目前都了解什么
But here we are. Catch me up. What do we know?
一架B-29轰炸机在北太平洋检测到了辐射
One of our B-29s over the North Pacific has detected radiation.
-拿到滤纸了吗  -都不用怀疑是什么情况
- Do we have the filter papers? - There's no doubt what this is.
-白宫还在怀疑  -恐怕只是一厢情愿
- White House says there's a doubt. - Wishful thinking, I'm afraid.
那是远程探测滤纸吗
Are those the long-range detection filter papers?
是原子弹试爆
It's an atomic test.
苏联人造出了核弹
The Russians have a bomb.
我们本应领先他们好几年  但是这...
We're supposed to be years ahead of them, but this...
你们在洛斯阿拉莫斯是干什么吃的
What were you guys doing in Los Alamos?
安保不是密不透风吗
Wasn't security tight?
-当然是  您并不在那里  -抱歉  博士
- Of course it was. You weren't there. - Forgive me, Doctor.
但我在场
But I was there.
现在可以考虑具体的引爆机制了
We can now consider the actual mechanics of detonation.
-有想法吗  -我把这种方法叫做射击
- Any ideas? - I call this shooting.
把一小块可裂变物质打进大球内部
We fire a chunk of fissionable material into a larger sphere
能量大到足以使之达到临界点
with enough force to achieve criticality.
-大家觉得呢  -我想的是内爆
- What do we think? Anyone? - I've been thinking about implosion.
球体周围包裹的炸药向内爆炸  压缩裂变物质
Explosives around the sphere blast inwards, crushing the material.
-我想就此研究一下  -我去找军备处
- I'd like to investigate that idea. - I'll talk to ordnance.
要来足够的炸药
Get you blowing things up.
-进展如何  -我也很高兴见到你
- Progress? - Nice to see you too.
这是我们的英国小分队
Meet the British contingent.
奥本海默博士  我是克劳斯·福克斯
Dr. Oppenheimer. Klaus Fuchs.
你做英国人多久了
How long have you been British?
从希特勒说我不是德国人起就是了
Since Hitler told me I wasn't German.
来吧  欢迎来到洛斯阿拉莫斯
Ah. Come, welcome to Los Alamos.
学校已经建成运营
The school's up and running.
-这是酒吧  -昼夜营业
- The bar. - Always running.
我还找到了减少后勤员工的办法
And I thought of a way to reduce support staff.
-那不是...  -希尔博夫人  没错
- Is that...? - Mrs. Serber, yes.
我为所有参与人员的配偶安排了工作
I've offered jobs to all the wives,
行政  图书馆  计算
admin, librarians, computation.
既精简了人员  又维系了家庭
We cut down on staff, keep families together.
-她们能胜任吗  -别胡说
- Are these women qualified? - Don't be absurd.
她们拥有这里最聪明的头脑
These are some of the brightest minds in our community.
而且已经获得了安全许可
And they're already security cleared.
我已经告知格罗夫斯将军
I've informed General Groves you've been holding
你每晚都办跨部门公开讨论
cross-divisional open discussions on a nightly basis.
立刻停止
Shut them down.
权限分隔至关重要
Compartmentalization is the key
-这样才能保证安全...  -只有负责人参与
- to maintaining security... - Only the top men.
不出意外他们也会与下属交流
Who presumably communicate with subordinates.
这些人并不愚蠢  他们能够保持谨慎
These men aren't stupid. They can be discreet.
我不喜欢
I don't like it.
你对什么都是这样  这算什么准则
You don't like anything enough for that to be a fair test.
每周一次  只有负责人参与
Once a week. Top men only.
-我想让我弟弟过来  -不行
- I'd like to bring my brother here. - No.
尼科斯
Nichols?
我还没有收到我的安全许可获批的消息
I still haven't heard that my security clearance has been approved.
-的确还没  -我明天要去芝加哥
- It hasn't. - I'm going to Chicago tomorrow.
你得等
Well, you should wait.
你知道纳粹领先我们两年时间吗
You are aware that the Nazis have a two-year head start?
奥本海默博士  您的安全许可
Dr. Oppenheimer, the fact that your security clearance
难以通过并不是我的错
is proving difficult to obtain is not my fault.
是您自己的
It's yours.
也许不是你的错  但应该由你解决
It may not be your fault, but it's your problem.
无论如何我要去
Because I'm going.
有多少人参与了这种
And how many people were in these, uh...
公开讨论
open discussions?
太多了  本应按规章做好权限分隔的
Too many. Compartmentalization was supposed to be the protocol.
我们当时在与纳粹竞速
We were in a race against the Nazis.
现在是与苏联竞速
And now the race is against the Soviets.
我们不发起比赛就不用比
Not unless we start it.
罗伯特  他们刚刚打响了发令枪
Robert, they just fired the starting gun.
他们用的是什么引爆装置
What's the nature of the device they detonated?
看数据可能是一枚钚内爆装置
Data indicates it may have been a plutonium implosion device.
正是你们在洛斯阿拉莫斯造的那种
Like the one you built at Los Alamos.
苏联人已经有了原子弹
The Russians have a bomb.
杜鲁门需要知晓下一步
Truman needs to know what's next.
下一步  军备谈判
What's next? Arms talks.
-军备谈判  -很显然
- Arms talks? - Obviously.
氢弹呢  杜鲁门知道吗
What about the Super? Does Truman even know about it?
我们有没有作过汇报
Did we brief him on that?
没有专门汇报过
Not specifically.
我们仍不知道氢弹在技术上是否可行
We still don't know if a hydrogen bomb is technically feasible.
好  就我所知这是泰勒提出的
Right, my understanding is that Teller proposed it.
-是的  -在洛斯阿拉莫斯提出的
- Yes. - At Los Alamos?
泰勒的设计非常不切实际
Teller's designs have always been wildly impractical.
按他的办法投弹要用牛车  而不是飞机
You'd have to deliver by oxcart, not airplane.
-奥比  -抱歉  劳伦斯博士
- Oppie! - I'm sorry, Dr. Lawrence,
您有话要说
do you want to comment?
没有
No.
因为如果氢弹能让我们再度领先
Because if it can put us ahead again,
美国总统就应该知道这件事
the President of the United States needs to know about it.
如果苏联人已经通过洛斯阿拉莫斯的间谍知道了
And if the Russians know about it already from a spy,
我们必须着手研究了
at Los Alamos, then we've got to get going.
没有证据表明洛斯阿拉莫斯存在间谍
There's no proof there was a spy at Los Alamos.
罗伯特
Robert.
他们的实验室在足球场底下
They put it under the football stadium?
场地早就停用了
The field's not in use anymore.
不相上下
Just as well.
-奥比  -费米博士
- Oppie! - Dr. Fermi.
你怎么样  还好吗
Come stai, tutto bene?
-我听说你坐拥一座小镇  -没错  欢迎参观
- I hear you've got a little town. - Yes, come and see.
在那种地方谁能正常思考
Who could think straight in a place like that, huh?
大家都会被逼疯的
Everybody will go crazy.
谢谢你的信任  西拉德
Thank you the vote of confidence, Szilard.
这些也值得记
Do we really... do we really need that in the notes?
你们要试验吗
Are you gonna try it out?
已经做过了
We did.
首次自持续链式核反应
The first self-sustaining nuclear chain reaction.
格罗夫斯没告诉你吗
Didn't Groves tell you?
没有
No.
奥本海默博士
Dr. Oppenheimer?
我找过人力
I tried personnel.
-他们问我会不会打字  -你会吗
- They asked if I could type. - Can you?
哈佛的化学研究生课程忘了教这个
Harvard forgot to teach that on the graduate chemistry course.
康登  让霍尼格夫人加入钚小组
Condon, put Mrs. Hornig here on the plutonium team.
你们去芝加哥干什么
What the hell were you doing in Chicago?
-参观大都会博物馆  -为什么
- Visiting the met. - Why?
-你不能...  -为什么
- You can't... - Why?
因为我们完全有权
Because we, we have every right...
你有什么权利我说了算  一点不多  一点不少
You have just the rights that I give you. No more, no less.
我们都是成年人  齐心协力做一个项目
We are adults trying to run a project here.
这太荒谬了
This is ridiculous.
说话啊
Tell him!
权限分隔是我们认同的规章制度
Compartmentalization is the protocol we agreed to.
我受够这个疯人院了  这种条件谁还能安心工作
Enough of this madhouse. Nobody can work under these conditions.
告诉你吧  大将军  我不干了
You know what? Generalissimo, I quit!
可太谢谢你了
Thanks for nothing.
没了他更好
Better off without him.
你不是更应该担心他的保密问题吗
Aren't you more concerned about his discretion out there?
找人做掉他就好了
We'll have him killed.
开玩笑的
I'm just kidding.
不必  他讨厌的是我  不是美国
No, he hates me, not America.
可是将军  不是所有人都像我一样有把柄可抓
You know, General, not everyone has levers to pull like mine.
我不太明白
I don't think I understand.
你招募我不是因为宽恕了我过去的左翼倾向
You didn't hire me despite my left-wing past.
恰恰因为我的过去你才招募了我
You hired me because of it.
这样你就能控制我
So you could control me.
不  我做事没有这么含蓄
No, I'm not that subtle.
我只是个普通的大头兵罢了
I'm just a humble soldier.
你既不普通  也不是大头兵
You're neither humble, nor just a soldier.
你在麻省理工学过工程学
You studied engineering at MIT.
-被你发现了  -既然我们已经互相理解
- Guilty as charged. - Well, now we understand each other,
也许你现在可以帮我拿到安全许可
perhaps you can get me my security clearance,
让我继续为你创造奇迹
so I can perform this miracle for you.
格罗夫斯将军
General Groves,
您在任命奥本海默博士的时候
were you aware of Dr. Oppenheimer's left-wing associations
是否了解他与左翼存在联系
when you appointed him?
我知道有人对此有所怀疑
I was aware that there were suspicions about him.
我知道他的身份背景极其自由派
I was aware he had a very extreme liberal background.
在你看来
In your opinion,
他是否有意识地做出过不忠于国家的行为
would he ever consciously commit a disloyal act?
如果他做过  那我会很惊讶
I would be amazed if he did.
所以你完全信任他的忠诚吗
So you had complete confidence in his integrity?
在洛斯阿拉莫斯是的
At Los Alamos, yes.
我真正了解他就是在那里
Which is where I really knew him.
你知道在这个项目中  你的安全官员曾建议你
Do you know that your security officers on the project
不要给奥本海默博士发放安全许可吗
advised you against the clearance of Dr. Oppenheimer?
要不是我坚持  他们不能  也不会给他安全许可
They could not, and would not, clear him until I insisted.
也就是说  你对奥本海默博士的
And it's safe to say that you had pretty good knowledge
-安全档案的内容了然于胸  -是的
- of Dr. Oppenheimer's security file. - I did.
那么今天我其实只剩下一个问题
Well, then there's only really one question
希望得到解答了
I need answered here today.
按照现行的原子能委员会准则
In light of the current AEC guidelines,
你今天还会给奥本海默博士发放安全许可吗
would you clear Dr. Oppenheimer today?
你手头有这个准则吗
Do you have the guidelines?
按照现行的原子能委员会准则
Under current AEC guidelines,
你今天还会给奥本海默博士发放安全许可吗
would you clear Dr. Oppenheimer today?
物理和新墨西哥州是吧
Physics and New Mexico, huh?
老天爷  这一路可真够远的
My god. What a trek.
所以你需要个联络员
That's why you need a liaison.
我要让洛马尼茨来干
I'm appointing Lomanitz.
你不会有事的  这边请  先生们
You're gonna be okay. This way, gentlemen.
-劳伦斯博士  -莱斯利
- Dr. Lawrence. - Leslie.
我想提醒你一句我们在伯克利谈的内容
I'd like to remind you what we talked about at Berkeley.
权限分隔  我完全理解
Compartmentalization, I understand completely.
伯克利向大家问好
Greetings from Berkeley.
我来是为了和大家通报我们的进展
I am here to update you on our progress
并听取大家的意见的
and solicit your input.
因此  我不得不分享几件
To do so, I am going to have to share a few things that
格罗夫斯将军不让我说的事
General Groves told me not to.
抱歉将军  我说的是我理解  而不是我同意
Sorry General, I said I understood, not that I agreed.
好了  先生们  说正事
Okay. Gentlemen, to business!
有传言说洛斯阿拉莫斯
There were rumors of espionage
-有间谍  -毫无根据
- at Los Alamos. - Unsubstantiated.
我听说项目里有
I'm told that there were communists
-共产党  -我们并没有明明知情还雇用...
- on the project. - We didn't knowingly employ...
我只想知道  他们中是否有人
I just want to know, were any of them involved
参与了关于氢弹的讨论
in discussions of the Super?
我似乎记得你要求让你弟弟来洛斯阿拉莫斯
I seem to remember you demanding your brother come to Los Alamos.
我弟弟那时候已经不是共产党了
My brother had left the party by then.
洛马尼茨呢
What about Lomanitz?
洛马尼茨从来不是洛斯阿拉莫斯的工作人员
Lomanitz was never employed at Los Alamos.
他只是联络员
He was a liaison.
我们的安保没有问题
Our security was tight,
前中校尼科斯很清楚这一点
as former Colonel Nichols well knows.
鉴于项目涉及的人员
Our security was as tight as it could be
我们的安保只能说尽可能严格
given the personalities involved,
但确实有人试图窃密
but attempts were made.
-这话是什么意思  -我们都看过他的档案
- What is that supposed to mean? - We've all read his file here.
难道还需要说吉恩·塔特洛克的事吗
Do we need to talk about Jean Tatlock?
或者薛瓦利埃事件
Or the Chevalier incident?
失陪
Excuse me.
洛马尼茨  一号线
Lomanitz, line one!
喂  罗西
Hello, Rossi.
什么
What?
好的  冷静
Okay, just calm down.
又有件麻烦事
There's been another screwup.
洛马尼茨被军队征召了
Lomanitz just got drafted.
我们正在打仗  博士
We are at war, Doctor.
别犯浑  尼科斯
Don't be an asshole, Nichols.
我们需要这孩子  把这件事解决了  行吗
We need this kid. Fix it, will you?
这事本就没搞错
It wasn't a mistake.
你的朋友洛马尼茨一直试图成立放射性实验室工会
Your friend Lomanitz has been trying to unionize the radiation lab.
-他保证过停下的  -但他没停
- He promised to quit all that. - Well, he hasn't.
伯克利的安全官员担心
The security officer at Berkeley is concerned
共党会通过那个工会渗入
about communist infiltration through that union,
-叫FA...  -FAECT
- the FA... - FAECT.
我下周过去的时候  我会...顺路去找他
While I'm there next week, I'll... drop in to see him.
你的安全许可证下来了
Your Q clearance came through.
重要的是
It's important
你不要再和一些可疑的人有牵连
you not maintain or renew any questionable associations.
博士  你当时是否认为
Doctor, did you think social contacts
你作为接触战争机密的人
between a person engaged on secret war work
与共产党人接触很危险
and communists was dangerous?
今时今日我对这种危险有了更深刻的认知
My awareness of the danger would be greater today.
那就是说  可以说在战争时期
I mean, it's fair to say that during the war years,
你觉得此类接触是有潜在危险的
you felt that such contacts were potentially dangerous.
可以想见是危险的  没错
Were conceivably dangerous, yes.
说真的
I mean, really!
公开的共产党人
Known communists.
听着...
Look...
一直以来我的脑海里都有许多秘密
I've had a lot of secrets in my head for a long time.
无论我与谁交往  我都不会谈起这些秘密
Doesn't matter who I associate with, I don't talk about those secrets.
你在你的声明中说
You said in your statement
1943年你必须去见吉恩·塔特洛克
that you had to see Jean Tatlock in 1943.
你离开了
You left.
一句话都没留
Not a word.
你觉得我会怎么想
What did you think that would do to me?
我写过信
I wrote.
里面一句有用的都没有
Pages of nothing.
你去哪里了
Where did you go?
-我不能告诉你  -为什么
- I can't tell you. - Why not?
因为你是个共产党
Because you're a communist.
你为什么必须去见她
Why did you have to see her?
我们离开前  她表示极其想见我
She had indicated a great desire to see me before we left.
那时我没能去见她  但我觉得她必须见到我
At that time I couldn't, but I felt that she had to see me.
她当时正在接受精神治疗  她非常难过
She was undergoing psychiatric treatment. She was extremely unhappy.
你弄清楚她为什么必须见你了吗
Did you find out why she had to see you?
因为她依旧爱着我
Because she was still in love with me.
你们共度了一夜  是吗
You spent the night together, didn't you?
是的
Yes.
你在我的生命中出现又离开
You drop in and out of my life,
也不用和我解释为什么
and you don't have to tell me why.
-这就是所谓的掌控权  -我也不想这样
- And that's power. - Not that I enjoy.
我宁愿在你需要的时候陪着你
I'd rather be here for you as you need.
但你如今有了更重要的事
But you have other priorities now.
我有了妻子和孩子
I have a wife and child.
你我都心知肚明我们在说的不是这个
That's not what either of us is talking about.
吉恩...你要我过来
Jean... you asked me to come.
我也很高兴我来了
And I'm glad I did.
但我之后不能再见你了
But I can't see you again.
那如果我需要你怎么办
But what if I need you?
你说过你一定会接的
You said you would always answer.
不说话了吗
Not a word?
你当时认为这符合安全规定吗
Did you think that consistent with good security?
事实上  是符合的
As a matter of fact, it was.
我什么都没说
Not a word.
在此之后  你还在何时见过她
When did you see her after that?
再也没见过了
I never saw her again.
我还能赶上最后一班火车回普林斯顿
I can make the last train back to Princeton.
吉蒂  我刚刚说的话我之前全都告诉过你
Kitty, I didn't say anything that I hadn't already told you.
但今天你可是向全世界宣告了  不是吗
Today you said it to history, didn't you?
这是个闭门听证会
This is a closed hearing.
就算他们不公开笔录  我敢肯定你也会的
If they don't release the transcript, I'm sure you will.
-我宣誓过的  -你对我也曾宣誓过
- I was under oath. - Well, you were under an oath to me
但你还是去见吉恩了
when you went to see Jean.
你知道吗  你...
You know, you...
你坐在那里  日复一日
You sit there, day after day,
任由他们把我们的生活撕成碎片
letting them pick our lives to pieces.
你为什么不反抗
Why won't you fight?
罗伯特  我不会让她作证的
Robert, I'm not putting her up there.
奥本海默博士  真是荣幸  快请坐
Dr. Oppenheimer! This is an honor. Please, take a seat.
不用了  我只是来看看我是否应该...
No need. I just wanted to check whether I should...
趁着我在这里和洛马尼茨谈谈
talk to Lomanitz while I'm here,
毕竟你们有所顾虑
given your concerns.
我得说这其实取决于你  教授
I'd say that's really up to you, Professor,
但如果是我  我会谨慎一些
but I'd be cautious.
明白
Understood.
对了  说到工会
Oh, and, um, as regards to the union,
我想提醒你们留意一个叫埃尔滕顿的人
I wanted to give you a heads up on a man named Eltenton.
提醒
A heads up?
是的  也许他值得留意  仅此而已
Yes, just that he might bear watching, is all.
我很乐意听听细节
I'd love to get more details.
我现在有安排  而且明天一早就要离开
I have an appointment now, and I leave early tomorrow.
明天您多早来都可以
Well, come back as early as you like.
既然您现在没空
Since you haven't time now.
你第二天早上过去了
You went back the next morning.
是的  我不得不去
I did. I had to, really.
这次在场的还有另一个人
This time there was another man.
他说他姓帕什
He said his name was Pash.
帕什  你见到了帕什上校
Pash. You met Colonel Pash?
帕什上校
Colonel Pash,
你能读一下你1943年6月29日的备忘录吗
could you please read from your memo dated June 29, 1943?
"对该对象的监视结果显示
"Results of surveillance conducted on subject
其可能存在的与共产党的联系
"indicate further possible Communist Party connections."
该对象面见了一个叫吉恩·塔特洛克的共产党
"Subject met with and spent considerable time
并与之共度了很长一段时间
"with one Jean Tatlock, a communist,
关于她的信息已附上"
"the record of whom is attached."
-对象指的是奥本海默博士吗  -是的
- The subject being Dr. Oppenheimer? - Yes.
你当时甚至还没见过他是吗
Whom you had not met?
当时没有  但不久之后就见到了
Not then, but soon after.
他是项目的安全主管  我不应该认识他吗
He's the head of security for the project. Shouldn't I know him?
不  他应该认识你
No, he should know you.
要我说我是绝不会让你和帕什共处一室的
I would never put you in a room with Pash.
为什么
Why not?
帕什第一次听说洛马尼茨的事时
When Pash first heard about Lomanitz,
他告诉联调局他打算绑架他
he told the FBI he was going to kidnap him,
把他带到一艘船上
take him out on a boat,
用苏联人的方式拷问他
and interrogate him in the Russian manner.
格罗夫斯将军交给了我一项任务
General Groves has placed in me a certain responsibility,
感觉就像是我有一个孩子但不能见他
and it's like having a child who I can't see,
只能遥控指挥
by remote control.
所以见到您本人真是...
So to actually meet you is...
-我不会占用您太多时间  -不不
- I won't take up too much of your time. - Oh, no.
完全不会  任何时间都可以
Not at all. Whatever time you choose.
约翰逊先生和我说了你俩昨天的对话
Mr. Johnson told me of the conversation you had yesterday,
我对此非常感兴趣  也担心了一整天
which I'm very interested in. It's had me worried all day.
是的  我不想在没得到许可的情况下
Yes, well, I didn't want to talk to Lomanitz
和洛马尼茨交谈
without authorization.
我感兴趣的不是这件事
That's not the particular interest that I have.
而是一件更加...
It's something a little bit more...
在我看来  更加严重的事
In my opinion, more serious.
然后当联调局指出
And then when the FBI pointed out
这样得来的信息法庭不会接受时
that such information wouldn't be admissible in court,
帕什清楚地表明
Pash made it clear he had no intention
任何可以指控他的证人  他都不会留活口
of leaving any witness left to prosecute.
幸好联调局打消了他这个念头
Now, the FBI talked him down,
但你要对付的就是这种人
but that's the man you're dancing with.
我了解到你听说有其他势力
I gather you've heard there are other parties
对放射性实验室的工作感兴趣
interested in the work of the radiation lab?
一名认识苏联领事的人
A man attached to the Soviet consul indicated,
通过中间人向该项目的成员表示
through intermediate people, to people on this project,
他愿意传递信息
that he was in a position to transmit information.
项目里怎么会有人想要这么做呢
Well, why would anyone on the project want to do that?
老实说  我明白也许有人认为
Frankly, I can see that there might be an argument
总司令应该与苏联通气
for the commander-in-Chief informing the Russians,
毕竟他们是我们的盟友  但是...
they're our allies, after all, but...
我不喜欢偷偷摸摸这么做
I don't like the idea of it going out the back door.
留意一下这件事也许没什么坏处
It might not hurt to be on the lookout for it.
你是这么和帕什说的
And you said that to Pash.
我是试图说明"苏联不是德国"
I was trying to put it in the context of "Russia's not Germany".
鲍里斯·帕什的父亲是一名东正教主教
Boris Pash is the son of a Russian Orthodox bishop.
他出生在美国
Born here,
但1918年回了苏俄与布尔什维克作战
but in 1918 he went back to Russia to fight the Bolsheviks.
这是一个亲手杀过共产党的人
This is a man who has killed communists with his own hands.
谁该不该得到信息这件事不由我评判
I'm not the judge of who should or should not have information.
我的职责是阻止信息非法泄露
It's my business to stop it from going through illegally.
您能说得更详细些吗
Could you be a little more specific?
有个人的名字我听过几次
There's a man whose name was mentioned to me, a couple of times,
埃尔滕顿
Eltenton.
他应该是壳牌公司的一名化学家
I believe he's a chemist who works at Shell.
他与他的一个朋友交流过
He talked to a friend of his,
这位朋友是项目里某人的熟人
who's an acquaintance of someone on the project.
然后你以为你说到这个程度  帕什就满足了
And you thought Pash would be satisfied with that?
我本意是把埃尔滕顿给他们
I was attempting to give them Eltenton
但又不引起更大的麻烦
without opening a can of worms.
我给他们编了个故事
I told them a cock-and-bull story.
-你当时对格罗夫斯将军也撒谎了吗  -没有
- Did you lie to General Groves, too? - No.
我向他坦白  我对帕什撒谎了
I admitted to him that I'd lied to Pash.
你还记得关于薛瓦利埃事件的那次谈话吗
Do you recall this conversation about the Chevalier incident?
我见过许多不同的版本...
I've seen so many versions of it, uh...
之前我并不迷惑  但如今显然开始迷惑了
Wasn't confused before, but I'm certainly getting there now.
-那么你的结论是什么  -他受到了典型的
- And what was your conclusion? - That he was under the influence
美式校园男生小团体思维的影响
of the typical American schoolboy attitude
觉得自己不能告发朋友
that there's something wicked about telling on a friend.
那么  能告诉我这个中间人是谁吗
Well now, might we know through whom the contact was made?
这会牵扯到和此事无关的人
That would involve people who are not to be involved in this.
这个人是计划里的一员吗
Is that someone a member of the project?
是教职人员  但没参与计划
A member of the faculty, yes, but not in the project, no.
所以埃尔滕顿
So Eltenton made his approach
通过伯克利的某个教职人员接触到了计划
through a member of the faculty here at Berkeley.
据我所知  是的
As far as I know, as far as I know, yes.
但可能  牵扯到不止一个人
But there... may have been... more than one person involved.
先生们  如果我...看起来不太配合
Gentlemen, if I... if I seem uncooperative,
我希望你们理解  因为我坚持
I think you can understand it's because of my insistence
不想让无辜的人陷入麻烦
on not getting innocent people into trouble.
你在努力保护你的朋友  谁来保护你
You're trying to protect your friend. Who's protecting you?
你可以
Well, you could.
-你告诉我他的名字  -如果你命令我  我会的
- If you gave me the name... - If you order me to, I'll do it.
这不对  罗伯特  你要自愿说出他是谁
That's a mistake, Robert. You need to volunteer this name.
他给你名字了吗
Did he give you the name?
-给了  -但不是当时就给了  是吗
- He did. - But not then, did he?
-不  -不  事实上是几个月后  对吗
- No. - No, in fact, it was some months later, wasn't it?
是的
It was.
-你觉得我很固执  -你确实
- You see me as persistent. - Well, you are...
你是很固执  但那是你的职责
you are persistent, but that is your job.
而我的职责是保护为我工作的人
And, and my job is to protect the people that work for me.
我们不想采取某些手段
Instead of us going on certain steps,
它们也许会引起你的注意
which may come to your attention...
让你感到不安
and be disturbing to you,
我希望能先和你讨论一下
I would like to discuss those with you first.
我并不是在制定计划  只是需要消化整件事
I'm not formulating a plan, I'll just have to digest the whole thing.
在你审问奥本海默博士
In the months in between your interview with Dr. Oppenheimer,
和他最终供出薛瓦利埃之间的几个月里
and his eventual naming of Chevalier,
你是否调动了资源
did you expend resources trying to find
-试图找出中间人的名字  -相当多的资源  是的
- the name of the intermediary? - Considerable resources, yes.
不知道是谁的情况下  我们的工作极为困难
Without the name, our job was extremely difficult.
你什么时候得知那个名字的
And when did you receive the name?
奥本海默供出名字的时候  我已经离开了
I was gone by the time Oppenheimer finally offered it up.
离开
Gone?
他们觉得我最好去欧洲
They felt my time would be better spent in Europe,
调查纳粹炸弹计划的情况
determining the status of the Nazi bomb project.
谁
Who did?
格罗夫斯将军
General Groves.
他把我调去了伦敦
He transferred me to London.
现在办圣诞派对有点早了
It's a little early for a Christmas party.
出事了
Something's up.
托尔曼走了
Tolman's been away.
去哪了
Where?
露丝不愿意说
Ruth won't tell.
拜托了  露丝
Come on, Ruthie.
你连我都不告诉  你还能告诉谁
If you can't tell me, who can you tell?
权限分隔  奥比
Compartmentalization, Oppie.
你怎么就觉得我会知道他在哪呢
What makes you think I know where he is, anyway?
因为在有事情的时候
Because you do a pretty good job
你总是知道托尔曼先生在哪
of knowing where Mr. Tolman is when it counts.
比如现在
Like now?
全体立正
Attention!
提前送各位的圣诞礼物
Early Christmas present for you all.
英国飞行员让我坐进了炸弹舱
The British pilot put me in the bomb bay.
他给我演示了氧气面罩  但我不会用
He showed me the oxygen, you know, but I messed it up.
他们在苏格兰给我开舱时  我已经失去了意识
Um, when they opened me up in Scotland, I was unconscious.
但我假装我在打盹
But I pretended I'd been napping.
大家玩得开心
Please enjoy your party.
-足够大吗  -大到结束这场战争吗
- Is it big enough? - To end the war?
结束所有战争
To end all war.
海森堡到哥本哈根找我
Uh, Heisenberg sought me out in Copenhagen.
真让人脊背发凉  我以前的学生为纳粹效力
It was chilling, my old student working for the Nazis.
他告诉了我一些事情  为了让我出山
He told me some things to draw me out.
铀持续的裂变反应
Sustained fission reactions in uranium.
这听起来更像是反应堆  而不是炸弹
That sounds more like a reactor than a bomb.
他提到气相扩散了吗
Did he mention gaseous diffusion?
他似乎更注重于重水
He seemed more focused on heavy water.
-作为缓和剂  -是的  不是用石墨
- As a moderator? - Yes, instead of graphite.
怎么了
What?
他方向错了
He took a wrong turn.
我们领先了
We're ahead.
再加上你在这里帮我们  尼尔斯
And with you here to help us, Niels...
抱歉先生们  让我们单独说几句好吗
Sorry, could you give us a moment, gentlemen?
我不是来帮忙的  罗伯特
I am not here to help, Robert.
我知道没有我你也能做到
I knew you could do this without me.
-那你为什么来  -来谈谈以后的事
- Then why did you come? - To talk about after.
你即将释放的威力将比纳粹还长久很多
The power you're about to reveal will forever outlive the Nazis.
世界还没做好准备
And the world is not prepared.
"即便没准备好应付石头下的蛇
"You can lift the stone
你也可以抬起它"
without being ready for the snake that's revealed."
我们要让政客们明白  这不是新武器
We have to make the politicians understand this isn't a new weapon.
这是新世界
It's a new world.
我在外面会尽我所能  但是你...
I'll be out there doing what I can, but you...
你是美国普罗米修斯
You're an American Prometheus.
你给了他们自毁的能力
The man who gave them the power to destroy themselves.
他们会敬重这一点
And they'll respect that.
你的工作才真正开始
Your work really begins.
抱歉  奥比  但有个电话
I'm sorry, Oppie, but there's a call.
从旧金山打来的
From San Francisco.
罗伯特
Robert!
Robert?
罗伯特
Robert.
老天  怎么回事
God, what's the matter?
发生什么了
What happened?
她父亲打了通电话
Her father called.
他昨天在浴缸里发现了她
He found her yesterday in the bath.
谁
Who?
她吃了药  留了遗书  没有署名
She's taken pills. Left a note, not signed.
她吃了巴比妥类药物  但她的血液里有水合氯醛
She took barbiturates, but there was chloral hydrate in her blood.
有一封遗书
There was a note.
吉恩·塔特洛克
Jean Tatlock?
我去见过她
We were together.
她说她需要我  我...
She said she needed me. I...
我告诉她我...
I told her I...
我不该...
I wouldn't...
我告诉她我...
I told her I...
不  是因为我  是因为我
No, it was me, it was me.
你不能自己做了坏事
You don't get to commit the sin
却让我们所有人都因为它的后果而怜悯你
and then have us all feel sorry for you that it had consequences.
马上振作起来
Now you pull yourself together.
这里的人都靠着你
You know, people here depend on you.
唐纳德  你能帮个忙吗
Donald, would you like to contribute here?
-拜托  帮帮我  -你只能靠自己  伙计
- Please, help me out. - You're on your own, pal.
鲍勃  我不会因为钚有放射性就辞职
Bob, I'm not quitting my job because plutonium is radioactive.
只是我们不知道它对女性生殖系统有多大影响
We just don't know what it might do to the female reproductive system.
你的生殖系统比我的暴露在外更多
Your reproductive system is more exposed than mine, presumably.
能不能别吵了
Can we please?
-内爆装置还不见踪影  -我们不能事事都急
- The implosion device is nowhere. - We can't rush everything.
奥比  说句话啊
Oppie, please.
着急和抓紧做是两码事  选一个吧
Well, there's rushing and there's getting on with it, so pick one.
等等  内德梅耶正在做他该做的
Wait, wait, wait. Neddermeyer is doing his job.
泰勒没干什么有用的  你没帮什么忙
Teller's not helping. You're not helping.
我问内爆透镜的计算结果都问几周了
I've been asking for calculations on the implosion lenses for weeks.
-让英国人福克斯来做嘛  -当然
- The British can do it. Fuchs. - Absolutely.
-那是你该做的  泰勒  -我要做研究
- It's your job, Teller. - I'm engaged in research.
研究我们甚至不会造的氢弹
On a hydrogen bomb we're not even building!
我不和这人合作
I won't work with that man.
让他走
Let him go.
-他太狂了  -我同意
- He's a prima donna! - I agree.
-他应该离开洛斯阿拉莫斯  -好了
- He should leave Los Alamos. - Okay.
基斯蒂  你顶替内德梅耶
Kisti, you replace Neddermeyer.
塞斯  我要你负责钚
Seth, I'm putting you on plutonium.
莉莉  你去配合基斯蒂  因为他需要你
Lilli, you go on for Kisti, because he needs you.
福克斯  你顶替泰勒的职责
Fuchs, you take Teller's role.
我要让你专门负责内爆装置
I'm putting you exclusively on the implosion device.
谁都不会离开洛斯阿拉莫斯
And no one is leaving Los Alamos.
-他们不让我走  -不  是我不让你走
- They won't let me leave! - No, I won't let you leave.
别管汉斯  别管裂变
Forget Hans, forget fission.
留在这里  想研究什么就研究什么
Stay here, research what you want.
聚变  氢弹  什么都行
Fusion, the hydrogen bomb, whatever.
-我们再碰面讨论  -你没时间碰面
- We'll meet to discuss it. - You don't have time to meet.
你现在是政客了  罗伯特
You're a politician now, Robert.
你很多年前就把物理抛于脑后了
You've left physics behind many, many years ago.
每周一次
Once a week.
一个小时  你和我
One hour, you and me.
把这个该死的栏杆升起来
Now raise this fucking barrier!
所以你在洛斯阿拉莫斯负责时  氢弹研究就开始了
So the Super was under development on your watch at Los Alamos?
是的
Yes.
但是战后  你试图否认其可行性
And yet, after the war, you tried to deny it was viable.
不不不  我指出了其中的技术难题
No, no, no. I pointed out technical difficulties with it.
你不是试图在苏联试爆后的
Didn't you try to kill it at the AEC meeting
-原子能委员会会议上扼杀氢弹项目吗  -不
- after the Russian bomb test? - No.
但那是原子能委员会的提议  不是吗
But that was the recommendation of the AEC, was it not?
是数小时讨论后得出的最优解
After hours of discussion about the best response.
氢弹的威力是原子弹的一千倍
An H-bomb is 1,000 times the power of an A-bomb.
其目标只能是最大的城市
Its only intended target would be the largest cities.
-这是种族灭绝式的武器  -伊西
- It's a weapon of mass genocide. - Izzy.
在地图这边画几个圈
Draw some circles on this side of the map,
圈出我国可能遭袭的地方  从纽约开始
where they would target us, starting with New York.
-行吧  -华盛顿特区
- That's fair. - D.C.
这是一种无法防御的进攻性武器
It's a weapon of attack with no defensive value.
-威慑  -威慑
- Deterrence. - Deterrence?
我们真的需要
Do we really need more deterrence
比现有的原子弹更大的威慑力吗
than our current arsenal of atomic bombs?
在三米还是三千米深的水中溺死  有什么区别
You, you drown in ten feet of water or 10,000, what's the difference?
我们已经足以溺死苏联  他们知道的
We can already drown Russia. They know it...
-现在他们可以溺死我们  -我们只是在升级
- Now they can drown us with... - We're just escalating...
如我所说  泰勒的设计
As I said, Teller's designs are still
依然像战时一样不切实际
as impractical as they were during the war.
氢弹是可以造出来的  奥比  你知道的
A hydrogen bomb can be made to work, Oppie. You know that.
我觉得我们不该把所有的资源都赌在那个概率上
I don't believe we should commit all our resources to that chance.
那你该怎样让杜鲁门打消美国人民的顾虑呢
Then how would you have Truman reassure the American people?
只需要通过对核能的国际管控
Simply by limiting the spread of atomic weapons
限制核武器的扩散
through international control on nuclear energy.
你是指世界政府
By which you mean world government.
联合国  正如罗斯福所设想
The United Nations, as Roosevelt intended.
我问的是杜鲁门该怎么做  好吗  世界已经变了
Well, I asked what Truman should do, right? The world's changed.
现在威胁我们生存的不是法西斯主义而是共产主义
It's not fascism but communism that now threatens our survival.
路易斯  你是否明白  如果我们造了氢弹
Lewis, do you understand, if we build a hydrogen bomb,
苏联人也不得不造他们自己的
the Russians will have no choice but to build their own?
他们有没有可能已经在造了
Could they be working on one already?
基于间谍从洛斯阿拉莫斯收集的情报
Based on information gathered from the spy at Los Alamos...
-洛斯阿拉莫斯没有间谍  -先生们
- No spy at Los Alamos. - Gentlemen...
-没有吗  -我们别偏题
- There wasn't? - Let's not get sidetracked.
我是说我们要通过承诺不造氢弹
I say we use this moment to gain concessions from the Russians
来获得苏联人的让步
by committing that we will not build a hydrogen bomb.
这样会透露氢弹是存在的
Thereby revealing its existence.
你似乎很确信他们已经知道了
Which you seem convinced they already know.
好了
Alright.
现在我希望委员会成员私下会面
At this point, I'd like the committee members to meet in privacy
敲定我们的提议
to finalize our recommendations.
我只是不确定你想要走上这条路
I'm just not sure you want to go down this route.
路易斯  不是不尊重  我们是咨询委员会
Lewis, with respect, we are the advisory committee.
我们应该给出我们的意见
We will give them our advice.
晚安
Good night.
奥本海默博士  您好
Dr. Oppenheimer? Hi.
威廉·波登  国会原子能联合委员会的
William Borden. Joint Committee on Atomic Energy.
是的  是的
Oh, yes, yes.
战争期间  我是一名飞行员
During the war, I was a pilot.
有一天夜里  我突袭回来  看到了惊人的一幕
One night, flying back from a raid, I saw an amazing sight.
像流星一样  一枚V2火箭冲向英国
Like a meteor. A V2 rocket headed to England.
我忍不住想象
I can't help but imagine what it will be
这样的敌军火箭载着核弹头会是什么样
for such an enemy rocket to carry an atomic warhead.
我们要确保这种情况不会发生
Let's make sure we're not the ones to make that possible.
奥比  你应该不想和施特劳斯作对吧
Oppie, I don't think you want to go up against Strauss.
如果我俩都发言  其他人会听我的
If we both speak, they listen to me.
他们听你说话像先知
When you speak, they hear a prophet.
他们听施特劳斯说话才像常人
When Strauss speaks, they hear themselves.
他们会听先知的
They'll listen to a prophet.
先知不能出错  一次都不行
A prophet can't be wrong. Not once.
你是否指责过奥本海默
Did you accuse Oppenheimer
蓄意破坏了氢弹的研发
of sabotaging the development of the Super?
我从来不会滥用"蓄意破坏"这类词
I was never one of those to bandy around terms like sabotage.
但波登先生会
But Mr. Borden was?
据我的理解  有可能
As I understand it, possibly.
波登先生是如何整理出一份如此详尽的起诉书的
How was Mr. Borden able to put together such a detailed indictment?
他当时已不是政府雇员
He was no longer a government employee,
但他似乎可以不受任何限制地
yet he appears to have had unlimited access
查阅奥本海默博士的档案
to Dr. Oppenheimer's file.
有可能是尼科斯先生把这些文件给他的吗
Might Mr. Nichols have given him access to the file?
还是原子能委员会的某个人
Or someone else at the AEC?
这是一个非常严重的指控  参议员
That's a very serious accusation, Senator.
你是不是在暗示
Is it your intention to suggest that
奥本海默博士背叛了美国
Dr. Oppenheimer is disloyal to the United States?
我一直认为  到现在仍然认为
I've always assumed, and still assume,
他忠于美国
that he's loyal to the United States.
我坚信  也会继续坚信这一点
I believe this, and I shall believe it,
除非我看到非常确凿的反驳证据
until I see very conclusive proof to the opposite.
你认为奥本海默博士是安全风险吗
Do you or do you not believe that Dr. Oppenheimer is a security risk?
恕我直言  希特勒在地堡里举枪自尽后
If I may, look, when Hitler blew his brains out in that bunker,
我认为这枚炸弹
it is my humble opinion that there is no need
就没必要再离开这个试验场地了
for that bomb to be seen anywhere except that test site.
我们至少应该停下来思考一下
Well, we at least have to take a moment to think about
手段是否还能证明目的的正当性  因为...
whether the means justify the ends any longer because...
德国就快投降了
Germany is about to surrender.
敌人不再是对人类最大的威胁
It's no longer the enemy who are the greatest threat to mankind.
我们的工作才是
It's our work.
希特勒死了  没错
Hitler's dead. It's true.
但日本人还在顽抗
But the Japanese fight on.
他们的战败似乎已成定局
Their defeat seems assured.
正要奔赴前线的大兵可不会这么认为
Not if you're a G.I. preparing to invade.
我们可以结束这场战争
We can end this war.
但要如何才能证明
But how do we justify
对人类使用这种武器是合乎道义的
using this weapon on human beings?
我们研究的是理论  对吧
We're theorists. Yes?
我们想象未来  但这一想象让我们恐惧
We imagine a future, and our imaginings horrify us.
他们只有理解了才会害怕
They won't fear it until they understand it,
而他们只有用过才能理解
and they won't understand it until they've used it.
洛斯阿拉莫斯的可怕秘密公诸于世后
When the world learns the terrible secret of Los Alamos,
我们在这里的工作将确保人类前所未有的和平
our work here will ensure a peace mankind has never seen.
这种建立在国际合作上的和平
A peace based on the kind of international cooperation
正是罗斯福一直设想的
that Roosevelt always envisaged.
-进展如何  -两年时间  花费十亿美元
- Progress? - Two years and a billion dollars' worth.
-难以估价  -不难  把账单加起来就知道了
- Hard to put a price on it. - Not really, just add up the bills.
农村免费包裹投递[接生]Rural free deliveries.
第一年就降生了80个新生儿
80 babies delivered the first year.
今年一个月就多出了10个孩子
This year we've had ten, a month.
节育问题有点超出我的管辖范围了  将军
Birth control is a little out of my jurisdiction, General.
-很明显  -将军
- Clearly. - General.
趴下  各位  福克斯  趴下
Head down, everybody. Fuchs, head down.
就是这样
That's the one!
两枚可引爆的炸弹
Two viable bombs.
我需要一个日期
I need a date.
九月
September.
七月
July.
大获成功  先生们
That's the sweet spot, gentlemen.
八月
August.
七月
July.
七月试爆
Tests in July.
但我需要我弟弟
But I need my brother.
弗兰克了解这片沙漠  他已经放下政治了
Frank knows the desert. He's left politics behind.
他已经和劳伦斯共事两年了
He's been working with Lawrence for two years now.
试验要叫什么
What do we call the test?
"猛击我的心吧  三位一体的上帝"[约翰·邓恩《圣十四行诗》]"Batter my heart, three-person'd God."
什么
What?
三位一体
Trinity.
你坚持要让你的弟弟弗兰克加入
You insisted on bringing on your brother Frank,
一个知名的共产党
a known communist.
前共党
Former communist.
你将一个知名的前共党...
You brought a known former communist...
引入了美国最机密也最重要的国防项目
onto America's most secret and important defense project.
我知道我的弟弟可以被信任  毋庸置疑
I knew my brother could be trusted. Absolutely.
你认为自己对团队中谁可以信任的判断
And you thought your judgment was sound
是正确的吗
on who on the team could be trusted?
福克斯  低头
Fuchs, head down.
好的  准备好了吗
Okay. Everybody ready?
希望你们有收获
I hope you learned something.
是的  知道了下次的安全距离要远得多
Yeah, we've learned we're gonna need to be a lot further away.
快点搞清楚
Well, figure it out, fast.
明天一早我们就去华盛顿
We leave for Washington in the morning.
要给他一个日期
We're going to give him a date.
这么大老远从芝加哥过来  利奥
You're a long way from Chicago, Leo.
我们再不采取行动  他们就要拿这个对付日本了
If we don't act now, they're going to use this thing against Japan.
我们预约了和杜鲁门会面  但被谁取消了
We booked a meeting with Truman, but somebody killed it.
你要去见战争部长
You're meeting the Secretary of War.
我们在造原子弹
Just because we're building it,
并不代表我们能决定怎么用
doesn't mean we get to decide how it's used.
历史会评判我们的  罗伯特
History will judge us, Robert.
我们在芝加哥起草了一份请愿书
In Chicago, we put together a petition.
我不...  我不要参与这事
I'm not... I'm not getting into this.
告诉我你的顾虑  我会传达
Just tell me your concerns, and I'll relate them.
我的顾虑  德国已经战败
My concerns? Germany's defeated.
日本独木难支
Japan's not going to hold out alone.
你怎么知道  是你把我们卷入这一切的
How could you know that? You got us into this.
你和爱因斯坦
You and Einstein,
写信给罗斯福说我们可以造一个炸弹
with your letter to Roosevelt saying we could build a bomb.
为了对抗德国
Against Germany.
武器制造不是这么简单的  西拉德
That's not how weapons manufacture works, Szilard.
奥比  你必须帮忙
Oppie, you have to help.
费米会出席会议  劳伦斯也会出席
Fermi's in the meeting. Lawrence is in the meeting.
他们不是你  你是科学界最厉害的推销员
They're not you. You're the great salesman of science.
你可以说服任何人
You can convince anyone of anything.
甚至你自己
Even yourself.
失陪了
Excuse me.
东京的大火造成十万人死亡  其中大部分是平民
The firestorm in Tokyo killed 100,000 people, mostly civilians.
我们做出这种事却没人抗议  让我很担心美国
I worry about America when we do these things and no one protests.
珍珠港事件
Pearl Harbor,
再加上太平洋地区持续三年的血战
and three years of brutal conflict in the Pacific,
极大地提高了美国民众的容忍度
buys a lot of latitude with the American public.
高到可以容忍投放原子弹吗
Enough to unleash the atomic bomb?
原子弹造成的破坏可能不会像东京轰炸那么严重
Uh, the A-bomb might not cause as much damage as the Tokyo bombings.
预估的数字呢
What are we estimating?
在一个中型城市
In a medium-sized city, uh...
两万到三万死亡
20,000 or 30,000 dead.
没错  但也不要低估
Yes, but don't underestimate
原子弹爆炸带来的心理冲击
the psychological impact of an atomic explosion.
三千米高的火柱
A pillar of fire, 10,000 feet tall,
方圆上下1.6千米的致命中子辐射效应
deadly neutron effects for a mile, in all directions,
仅通过一个装置
from one single device.
从一架隐蔽的B-29轰炸机上
Dropped from a barely-noticed B-29,
投下的原子弹将会是...
the atomic bomb will be...
神力的骇人展示
a terrible revelation of divine power.
果真如此的话  这将是决定性的一击
If that's true, it would be definitive.
二战将会结束
World War II would be over.
我们的大兵也就可以回家了
Our boys would come home.
打击军事目标吗
Military targets?
但没有足够大的军事目标
But there aren't any big enough.
命脉军工厂怎么样
Perhaps a vital war plant,
工人居住在附近的那种
with workers housed nearby.
我们可以发布警告  减少平民伤亡
And we could issue a warning to reduce civilian casualties.
他们为了击落那架飞机  会用上一切武器
They'd send everything they have up against us,
到时候坐在机舱里的人是我
and I'd be up in that plane.
如果我们事先宣布了  炸弹没能爆炸
If we announce it, and it fails to go off,
迫使日本投降的任何机会也就烟消云散
we'd scupper any chance of a Japanese surrender.
没有别的办法向日本展示核弹的效果
Is there no way to demonstrate a bomb to Japan
迫使其投降吗
to provoke surrender?
我们打算以最清楚明确的方式展示效果
We intend to demonstrate it in the most unambiguous terms.
展示两次
Twice.
第一次是为了展示武器的威力
Once to show the weapon's power,
第二次是为了表明我们可以扔到他们投降为止
and a second to show that we can keep doing this until they surrender.
我们列出了12个城市
We have a list of 12 cities to choose from.
抱歉  是11个
Sorry, 11.
我从中删掉了京都
I've taken Kyoto off the list,
因为这座城市对日本人民具有重要的文化意义
due to its cultural significance to the Japanese people.
还有我和夫人的蜜月是在那度的
Also, my wife and I honeymooned there.
那座城市了不起
It's a magnificent city.
简单点说  先生们
Let me make this simple for you, gentlemen.
根据我手上无法向各位透露的情报
According to my intelligence, which I cannot share with you,
日本人不会投降
the Japanese people will not surrender,
不管在什么情况下
under any circumstances,
除非我们成功全面入侵日本本土
short of a successful and total invasion of the home islands.
但这样许多人将丧命  无论是美国人还是日本人
Many lives would be lost, American and Japanese.
向日本城市投原子弹将能挽救生命
The use of the atomic bomb on Japanese cities will save lives.
前提是我们保留道德优势
If we retain moral advantage.
-怎么说  -如果我们使用这个武器
- How so? - Well, if we use this weapon
而未通知我们的盟友  他们会把这视为威胁
without informing our allies, they'll see it as a threat,
我们会陷入军备竞赛
and we'll be in an arms race.
对苏联人我们能坦诚到什么程度
How open can we be with the Soviets?
保密无法阻止苏联人造出原子弹
Secrecy won't stop the Soviets from becoming part of the atomic world.
-情报显示他们没有铀  -情报错了
- We've been told they have no uranium. - You've been misinformed.
苏联造出核弹只是时间问题
A Russian bomb is a matter of time.
战争结束后  这一项目仍要继续全速推进
The program needs to continue at full pace after the war.
史汀生部长  恕我直言
Secretary Stimson, if I may,
并非所有参与项目的科学家都同意
not all scientists on the project are in agreement.
事实上  现在也许是时候考虑其他意见了
In fact, this might be a moment to consider other opinions.
如果你和科学家们交流...
If you talk to scientists...
曼哈顿计划一开始
The Manhattan Project has been plagued
就备受某些不够可靠
from the start by certain scientists of...
忠诚度值得怀疑的科学家们的侵扰
doubtful discretion, and uncertain loyalty.
其中一位最近甚至试图接触总统
One of 'em just tried to meet with the President.
现在  我们还需要他们
Now, we need these men,
但一旦核弹完成
but as soon as it's practical,
我们就应该立即将这些科学家从项目中剔除
we should sever any such scientists from the program.
你不赞成吗  博士
Wouldn't you agree, Doctor?
如果苏联造出核弹不可避免
If a Russian bomb is inevitable,
也许我们应该邀请他们的顶尖科学家参加三位一体
perhaps we should invite their top scientist to Trinity.
杜鲁门总统并不打算让斯大林参与原子弹项目
President Truman has no intention of raising expectations
也不想提高这方面的期望
that Stalin be included in the atomic project.
向他通知我们的突破
Informing him of our breakthrough,
并将其作为赢得战争的手段
and presenting it as a means to win the war,
无需做出无法兑现的承诺
need not make unkeepable promises.
但是  七月的波茨坦和平会议
But, the Potsdam Peace Conference in July
将是杜鲁门总统最后一次进行这样对话的机会
will be President Truman's last chance to have that conversation.
到时你能给我们一枚能用的炸弹吗
Can you give us a working bomb by then?
当然
Absolutely.
我们会在会议前进行试爆
We will test fire before the conference.
试爆点
Ground zero.
北方  南方和西方九千米各有一处观测点
Observation posts at 10,000 yards, north, south, and west.
-在哪操作引爆  -南方  九千米
- Where do we trigger from? - South, 10,000.
大本营在南方约16千米处
And base camp is ten miles south here.
32千米外的那座山上还有一个远端观测点
And there's a further observation post on that hill, 20 miles away.
那是在做什么  弗兰克  触发线不是早埋好了
What's that, Frank? Trigger lines already went in.
空军要求为他们的B-29轰炸机装一排灯
The Air Force requested a line of lights for their B-29.
什么B-29  我们的炸弹在塔上
What B-29? Our bomb's on the tower.
他们想利用这次试验
They want to use the test
-确认安全操作距离  -太冒险了
- to confirm a safe operating distance. - That's risky.
总比不上往日本投核弹的时候
But not as risky as dropping one over Japan,
还得祈祷我们没把爆炸半径算错
and hoping that we were right about the blast radius.
别让他们拖慢进度  我们在15号就要引爆
Don't let 'em slow us down, we're firing on the 15th.
-15号  不是...  -就是15号
- The 15th? That's not... - The 15th.
15号
15th.
我会在南观测点这里
So I'll be here at South Observation Point
和弗兰克还有基斯蒂亚科夫斯基一起
with Frank and Kistiakowsky.
你们将被分配到大本营
You'll all be assigned to Base Camp,
西观测点或是远端观测点
West Observation, or Far Observation.
小心用刀
Careful with that knife.
这些是安全距离吗
Are those safe distances?
这些距离是基于你的计算
They're based on your calculations.
是时候亲自站在你的科学身后了  汉斯
Time to stand behind your science, Hans. Literally.
辐射云呢
What about the radiation cloud?
没有强风的情况下  应该会在三到五千米内沉降
Without high winds, it should settle within 2-3 miles.
疏散措施也已就位
Evacuation measures are in place.
但我们需要能见度  所以天气必须好
But we need good weather for visibility, so it has to be fine.
都出去
Everybody out!
我们15号夜里进行  不能再晚了
We go on the night of the 15th. It's a hard deadline.
有问题就现在提
So if anyone has anything, speak now.
好的  停  停  所有人  垫子
Okay, stop, stop! Everybody, mattresses.
把垫子放这里  正下方
Put the mattress there, underneath.
我们还需要做最后一次内爆试验
We could use a final implosion test.
-没什么坏处  -做吧
- It couldn't hurt. - Do it.
还有什么能阻止我们的吗
Is there anything else that might stop us?
要试爆了  是不是
It's happening, isn't it?
我会捎个信的
I'll send a message.
如果成功
If it's gone our way:
"收床单"
"Take in the sheets."
罗伯特
Robert.
祝你好运
Break a leg.
看
Look.
奥比非常保守地选了只有三千吨的奖券
Oppie's taken a very modest three kilotons.
-泰勒选了四万五千吨  -两万吨
- Teller's view is 45. - 20!
两万吨TNT当量
20,000 tons of TNT.
有人想要这张吗  会出现把大气层点着的副反应
And does anyone want the side action on atmospheric ignition?
你是说我们不得不推迟吗
Are you saying we'll have to delay?
我是说  谨慎的做法是推迟
I'm saying it would be prudent.
这场暴风雨已经到试验场了吗
This weather, has it reached the site?
贝特打来告诉你内爆试验失败了
Bethe is calling to tell you the implosion test failed.
喂  汉斯  是的  他在这
Hello, Hans? Yes, he's here.
是的
Yes.
是他错了吗
Is he wrong?
-不是  -不是吗
- No. - No?
不是
No.
所以我们是要试一枚哑弹吗
So we're about to fire a dud?
-不是  -解释啊
- No. - Explain!
我无法解释  我...
Well, I can't. I just, I...
我就是知道内爆透镜一定会成功
I just know, I know the implosion lenses will work.
如果我们点燃引爆装置却未引发反应
If we fire these detonators and they don't trigger a reaction,
这两年生产的钚就全都会散落在白沙国家公园
two years' worth of plutonium will be scattered across White Sands.
我用一个月工资和你赌十块  能引爆
A month of my salary against ten bucks says it lights.
老天
Oh, Jesus!
试爆点风力增强  雨势不变  电闪雷鸣
The wind's pickin' up at zero, not the rain. Lightning's circling.
就这天气  还想让你的人
Think it might be time to tell your men to get away
离开架设着核弹的钢架台吗
from the steel tower with the atomic bomb?
我们去南观测点
Let's get to South Observation.
让他们撤  我们可以到那里再做决定
Pull 'em out, and we can make our determination there.
团队已经两晚没合眼了
The team hasn't slept in two nights!
如果我们叫停  保证核弹安全
If we stand down and make the bomb safe,
得花好几周才能再次准备好
we won't be back here for weeks!
就会错过波茨坦会议
And we'll miss Potsdam!
我要在7点前告诉杜鲁门  我们快错过时机了
I gotta get word to Truman by seven, our window's closing.
-现在是怎么回事  -暴雨  狂风  闪电
- What is this doing? - Raining, blowing, lightning.
-还要多久  该死  -坚持住
- For how long, damnit? - Holdin' strong!
黎明前就会停
It'll break before dawn.
-你怎么知道  -我了解这片沙漠
- How could you know that? - I know this desert.
暴风雨在夜间减弱  在黎明前就能停
Storm cools overnight. Just before dawn, storm breaks.
你也许说得对
You could be right,
-但要尽可能迟一点  -五点半
- but schedule as late as possible. - Five-thirty.
签字画押  要是你错了  我就绞死你
Sign your forecast. If you're wrong, I'll hang you.
-通知全体  五点半  -五点半  五点半
- Tell 'em all. Five-thirty. - Five-thirty, five-thirty!
三年  四千人  二十亿美元
Three years, 4,000 people, two billion dollars.
这要是没爆炸
Well, if it doesn't go off,
我俩全完了
we're both finished.
我赌三千吨
I'm betting on three kilotons.
再少  他们就感受不到它的威力了
Anything less, they won't get what it is.
费米说点燃大气层是什么意思
Now, what did Fermi mean by, uh, atmospheric ignition?
我们曾一度认为  核装置的链式反应
Well, we had a moment where it looked like the chain reaction
也许永远不会停
from an atomic device might never stop.
点燃大气层
Setting fire to the atmosphere.
为什么费米还搞这个附加赌注
Why's Fermi still taking side bets on it?
算是黑色幽默吧
Call it gallows humor.
等等  就是说当我们按下那个按钮时
Wait, are we saying there's a chance that when we push that button,
有可能会毁灭世界吗
we destroy the world?
我们过去三年的研究并不支持这一结论
Nothing in our research over three years supports that conclusion,
除非是小概率事件
except as the most remote possibility.
-多小  -概率几近于零
- How remote? - Chances are near-zero.
几近于零
Near-zero?
只有理论  还想要什么呢
What do you want from theory alone?
是零最好
Zero would be nice.
确切来说  1小时...
In exactly one hour...
58分钟后  我们就知道了
and 58 minutes, we'll know.
天气正在转好
It's letting up.
部队已经离开试爆点  他们正在赶往这里
The arming party's left zero, they're heading this way.
打开开关
Throw on your switches.
掉转车头  做好紧急疏散的准备
Turn the cars! Ready for emergency evacuation.
...焊工镜片  各就各位
...welder's glass. Everybody take their places.
每人都拿一个焊工镜片
Everybody take a welder's glass!
20分钟
20 minutes.
20 minutes!
20分钟
That's 20!
放我腿上谢谢
On the leg, please.
-费曼  -不用了
- Feynman? - No.
车玻璃能阻挡紫外线
The glass stops the UV.
要是玻璃碎了可怎么办呢
What stops the glass?
我去大本营了
I'm heading to base camp.
祝你好运
Best of luck.
罗伯特
Robert?
尽量别把世界给炸了
Try not to blow up the world.
盯住那个指针
Watch that needle.
如果引爆装置没充电
If the detonators don't charge,
电压掉到一伏以下
and the voltage drops below one volt,
就按那个按钮中止  明白了吗
you hit that button, you abort. Understood?
明白了
Understood.
两分钟后引爆
Two minutes to detonation.
全体趴下
Everybody down!
看到山上反光之前不要转身
Do not turn around until you see light reflected on the hills.
然后只能通过焊工镜片观察爆炸
Then look at the explosion only through your welder's glass.
90秒后引爆
90 seconds to detonation.
80秒后引爆
80 seconds to detonation.
搽上了吗
Is it rubbed in?
是的
Yeah.
60秒后引爆
60 seconds to detonation.
这些事让人揪心
These things are hard on your heart.
30秒
30 seconds.
引爆装置充电完毕
Detonators charged!
17.
16.
15.
14.
13.
12.
11.
Ten.
Nine.
Eight.
Seven.
Six.
Five.
Four.
Three.
Two.
One.
"如今  我已成为死神"
"And now I am become Death...
"世界的毁灭者"
the destroyer of worlds."
成功了
It worked.
你欠我十美元
You owe me ten dollars!
-快拿来  -我愿赌服输  基斯蒂
- Come on! - I... I'm good for it, Kisti.
确实
You are!
是的  你确实
Yes, you are!
立刻给我接波茨坦
Get me Potsdam right away.
捎个信给吉蒂
Get a message to Kitty.
-我们什么都不能说  -告诉她收床单
- We can't say anything. - Tell her to take in the sheets.
-喂  -喂  吉蒂吗
- Hello? - Hi, Kitty?
什么什么  夏洛特  你说你说
What? What? Charlotte? Charlotte, go ahead. Go ahead.
我不太清楚
Well, I don't know,
他就告诉我让你收床单
he just said to tell you to bring in the sheets.
吉蒂
Kitty?
吉蒂  吉蒂你还在听吗
Kitty? Kitty, are you still there?
如果在过高的空中引爆
If they detonate it too high in the air,
爆炸威力不会这么强
the blast won't be as powerful.
恕我直言  奥本海默博士  接下来就由我们负责了
With respect, Dr. Oppenheimer, we'll take it from here.
杜鲁门在波茨坦跟斯大林通气了吗
Did Truman brief Stalin at Potsdam?
"通气"有点夸张了
"Brief" would be an overstatement.
他提到了一种颇具威力的新型武器
He referred to a powerful new weapon.
斯大林...希望我们用它对付日本
Stalin... hoped we'd use it against Japan.
就这样吗
That's it?
罗伯特  我们已经给了他们王牌
Robert, we've given them an ace.
打牌的是他们
It's for them to play the hand.
你打算6号用吗
You're aiming for the sixth?
这取决于太平洋司令
It's up to the CO in the Pacific.
要我和你一起去华盛顿吗
Should I come with you to Washington?
去做什么
What for?
那你有消息随时告诉我
Well, you keep me informed.
当然
Of course.
尽我所能
As best I can.
日本人如果知道接下来发生的事会投降吗
Would the Japanese surrender if they knew what was coming?
我不清楚
I don't know.
你看过西拉德的请愿书吗
Have you seen Szilard's petition?
西拉德怎么可能了解日本人
How the hell does Szilard know about the Japanese?
你不打算签吧
You're not signing it, are you?
很多人签了  许多
Many people have. A lot of people.
爱德华...
Edward...
我们是造了这枚炸弹  但这并没有赋予我们
the fact that we built this bomb does not give us any more,
任何多于常人的权利或责任
any more right or responsibility
来决定如何使用它
to decide how it's used than anyone else.
但我们是唯一知道它的人
But we're the only people who know about it.
我把学术界的各种声音告诉过史汀生
I've told Stimson the various opinions of the community.
但你怎么说
But what's your opinion?
一旦使用...
Once it's used...
核战争  也许...
nuclear war, perhaps...
所有战争...
all war...
变得难以想象
becomes unthinkable.
直到有人造出更大的
Until somebody builds a bigger one.
我以为他们会打电话
I thought they would call.
这才5号
It's only the fifth.
在日本  是6号了
In Japan, it's the sixth.
夏洛特
Charlotte?
打给格罗夫斯试试
Try Groves.
有消息吗
Anything?
-夏洛特  -杜鲁门在广播
- Charlotte? - Truman's on the radio.
16小时前
16 hours ago,
一架美国战机
an American airplane
在广岛投下一枚炸弹
dropped one bomb on Hiroshima,
彻底摧毁了这座城市的军工生产能力
and destroyed its usefulness to the enemy.
这枚炸弹的威力
The bomb has more power
超过两万吨TNT
than 20,000 tons of TNT.
这是一枚原子弹
It is an atomic bomb.
这是对宇宙基本力量的运用
It is a harnessing of the basic power of the universe.
格罗夫斯在一号线
Groves on one.
将军
General?
我为你感到非常骄傲  为你领导的所有人
I'm very proud of you, and all of your people.
一切顺利吗
It went alright?
据说是一次爆炸式的成功
Apparently it went with a tremendous bang.
为此这里每个人都相当高兴
Well, everyone here is feeling reasonably good about it.
这一路过来不容易
It's been a long road.
我认为我做过最明智的事
I think one of the wisest things I ever did
就是选了你当洛斯阿拉莫斯的负责人
was when I selected the director of Los Alamos.
我们花了这二十多亿美元
We have spent more than two billion dollars
全押在历史上最大的科学赌博上
on the greatest scientific gamble in history,
然后我们赢了
and we have won.
奥比  奥比  奥比
Oppie! Oppie! Oppie!
全世界...
The world...
将铭记这一天
will remember this day.
现在还无法
It's too soon to...
现在还无法确定
It's too soon to determine
投弹的最终结果
what the results of the bombing are.
不过我敢打赌  日本人肯定受罪了
But I'll bet the Japanese didn't like it.
我非常自豪
I'm so proud.
为你们的成就而自豪
So proud of what you have accomplished.
可惜当时没来得及用它对付德国人
I just wish we had it in time to use against the Germans.
奥本海默博士
Dr. Oppenheimer?
照片不错
Nice picture.
杜鲁门总统可以见你了
President Truman will see you now.
奥本海默博士  幸会
Dr. Oppenheimer, it's an honor.
-总统先生  -请坐
- Mr. President. - Please.
谢谢
Thank you.
伯恩斯部长
Secretary Byrnes.
成为全世界最有名的人  感觉怎么样
How's it feel to be the most famous man in the world?
你拯救了很多美国人的生命
You helped save a lot of American lives.
-我们在广岛的行动...  -还有长崎
- What we did at Hiroshima was... - And Nagasaki.
当然
Obviously.
因为你的发明  我们的士兵才安全归来了
Your invention let us bring our boys home.
不能说是我的发明
Well, it was hardly... my invention.
《时代》封面上的人是你
It was you on the cover of Time.
吉姆说  你担心我们和苏联展开军备竞赛
Jim tells me you're concerned about an arms race with the Soviets.
是的
Ah, yes, ah...
这个...
Well, um...
现在是时候
it's that, uh, now is our chance to secure...
就原子能开展国际合作了
international cooperation on atomic energy,
我担心
and-and-and I'm concerned...
你知道苏联什么时候能拥有原子弹吗
Do you know when the Soviets are gonna have the bomb?
我没法给出准确的...
I don't think I could give a...
永不
Never!
Never.
总统先生  苏联拥有优秀的物理学家
Mr. President, the Russians have good physicists,
-和丰富的资源  -还"丰富的"
- and, and abundant resources... - Abundant?
没错
Yes.
我不这么想
I don't think so.
他们会倾尽全力...
Well, they'll put everything they have in...
听说你要离开洛斯阿拉莫斯
I hear you're leaving Los Alamos.
该怎么处理它呢
What should we do with it?
还给原住民
Give it back to the Indians.
奥本海默博士
Dr. Oppenheimer...
如果你对苏联人的判断是对的
if what you say about the Soviets is true,
我们必须扩建实验室  而不是把它关掉
we have to build up Los Alamos, not shut it down.
总统先生
Mr. President...
我感觉自己的手上沾满鲜血
I feel that I have blood on my hands.
你以为广岛
You think anyone in Hiroshima, or...
或长崎有人在乎原子弹是谁造的吗
Nagasaki, gives a shit who built the bomb?
他们在乎的是投弹的人
They care who dropped it.
是我
I did.
广岛与你无关
Hiroshima isn't about you.
奥本海默博士
Dr. Oppenheimer.
别再让那个爱哭鬼来了
Don't let that crybaby back in here!
罗伯特明白了  内疚根本没用
Robert saw that hand-wringing got him nowhere.
当我见到他时
By the time I met him,
他已经完全接受了"原子弹之父"的声誉
he'd fully embraced his "Father of the Bomb" reputation
并利用自己的身份影响政策
and used his profile to influence policy.
博士  战后几年
Doctor, in the years following the war,
你是否对美国的原子能政策
would you say that you exerted a great influence
施加了重大影响
on the atomic policies of the USA?
"重大"有点夸张了
I think "great" would be an overstatement.
是吗  就说说同位素问题吧
Really? I mean, look at the issue of isotopes.
不正是你本人
Were you not personally responsible for
扫清了所有反对同位素出口的意见吗
destroying all opposition to their export?
造核武器还可能用到一瓶啤酒
...could use a bottle of beer in making atomic weapons.
的确会用到
In fact, you do.
我是发言人
I was the spokesman,
但科学家们的意见是一致的
but the opinion among scientists was unanimous.
随着麦卡锡主义崛起
All along, with McCarthy on the rise,
他明白自己有很多弱点
he knew he was vulnerable.
他弟弟上了全国所有大学的黑名单
His brother was blacklisted by every university in the country.
洛马尼茨沦落为铁路工人  去铺铁轨
Lomanitz wound up working the railroad, laying track.
薛瓦利埃被迫流亡
Chevalier went into exile.
但这都没有阻止罗伯特
But none of that stopped Robert
推动总顾问委员会提案军备控制
from pushing the GAC to recommend arms control,
而不是研发氢弹
instead of the H-Bomb.
当杜鲁门否决提案时  他几近崩溃了
He was devastated when Truman rejected their recommendation.
我太想念理查德了
I miss Richard more than I can bear.
我知道  露丝  我知道
I know, Ruth. I know.
幸好他看不到现在这番景象
I'm just glad he didn't live to see where this has all gone.
寿星要来幸灾乐祸了
Here comes the birthday boy, to gloat...
保重
Have fun.
罗伯特  我儿子和他未婚妻
Robert, my son and his fiancée
非常想认识原子弹之父
are desperate to meet the father of the atomic bomb, so...
你们好
Hello.
现在不方便吗
Is this a bad time?
你觉得呢  路易斯
What do you think, Lewis?
我觉得你肯定大受打击
Well, I think it must have been a blow for you.
是全世界大受打击
For the world.
世界  福克斯和世界有什么关系
The world? What does Fuchs mean to the rest of the world?
福克斯
Fuchs?
克劳斯·福克斯
Klaus Fuchs?
坏了  你还没听说
Oh dear. You haven't heard.
克劳斯·福克斯  那个英国科学家
Klaus Fuchs, the British scientist
你把他分配进洛斯阿拉莫斯的爆炸团队
that you put onto the implosion team at Los Alamos.
他其实是...
Turns out he was...
他一直在为苏联传递情报
He was spying for the Soviets the whole time.
很遗憾
I'm sorry.
福克斯的身份暴露后
After the truth about Fuchs came out,
联调局升级了对他的监视措施
the FBI stepped up surveillance on him.
他知道自己的电话被窃听
He knew his phone was tapped.
出行被跟踪
He was followed everywhere.
垃圾被检查
His trash picked through.
但他依然坚持直抒己见
But he never stopped speaking his mind.
信念坚定
A man of conviction.
也许他认为  名誉可以保护自己
And maybe he thought fame could actually protect him.
艾森豪威尔上台后  他看到了一个新的机会
When Eisenhower took office, he saw one more chance.
他抓住了
He took it.
可以把美国和苏联比作
America and Russia may be likened...
一个瓶子里的两只蝎子
to two scorpions in a bottle.
双方都能将对方置于死地
Each capable of killing the other,
同时承担着丧命的风险
but only at the risk of his own life.
这项政策有很多方面
Now, there are various aspects of this policy...
很多科学家都指责我
A lot of scientists blame me,
但我该怎么保护他呢
but how was I supposed to protect him?
过于秘密  不便讨论
...are too secret for discussion.
坦率是唯一的出路
Candor is the only remedy.
华盛顿的官员应该开始
Officials in Washington need to start
和美国人民坦诚相待了
leveling with the American people.
这就是敌人压倒罗伯特的最后一根稻草
That was the last straw for Robert's enemies.
所以他被迫失去了安全许可
So he had to lose his security clearance.
也失去了信誉
And with it, his credibility.
他们怎么能这么做
But how could they do it?
他可是战争英雄
He was a war hero.
他已经公开了自己的过去
He'd already told everyone about his past.
是波登挖出来的
Borden dredged it all up.
波登怎么能拿到奥本海默的联调局档案
How could Borden get access to Oppenheimer's FBI file?
会不会是尼科斯
Could it have been Nichols?
不  我不认为他会这么做
No, I can't imagine he'd do that.
不论是谁  他都燃起了一场大火
Whoever did unleashed a firestorm
从白宫一路烧到
that burned a path in the White House,
我在原子能委员会的办公桌前
right to my desk at the AEC.
你看到他们的态度了  对吧
You seen 'em in there, right?
我干了一辈子才终于有了今天
I've worked my whole life to get here.
美国内阁成员
The cabinet of the United States of America,
现在  在全国人民面前
and now, in front of the entire country,
他们想把我赶回原来的位置
they want to put me back in my place.
卑微的卖鞋人
A lowly shoe salesman.
路易斯  我们能赢
Lewis, we can win this thing.
我们可以让参议院认识到
I think we can get the Senate to grasp
你履行了职责  虽然很令人痛苦
that you did your duty, painful though it was.
-希尔会对我们有利吗  -没问题
- Now, will Hill's testimony back us up? - Hill will be fine.
我和他不熟
Not really I know him,
但他在芝加哥时是西拉德的手下
but he was one of Szilard's boys in Chicago.
他们永远不会原谅罗伯特
And they'd never forgave Robert
没有支持反对轰炸日本的请愿
for not supporting the petition against bombing Japan.
这是投弹后31天拍摄的
This was taken 31 days after the bombing.
方圆1.6千米之内  街上所有人
Virtually everyone in the streets, for nearly a mile around,
基本都立即被烧焦了
was instantly and seriously burned.
日本人说  很多人穿着有条纹的衣服
The Japanese spoke of people who wore striped clothing upon,
皮肤被烧成了条状
whom the skin was burned in stripes.
很多人自以为很幸运
There were many who thought themselves lucky,
爬出被炸毁的房子
who climbed out of the ruins of their homes,
只受了轻伤
only slightly injured.
但他们还是死了
But they died anyway.
他们死于几天或几周之后
They died days, or weeks later,
死于爆炸时释放出的
from radium-like rays emitted in great numbers
大量类似镭辐射的射线
at the moment of the explosion.
你看过这篇垃圾报道了吗
Did you read this crap in the papers?
有个英国物理学家说
A British physicist is saying
原子弹爆炸不是第二次世界大战的结束
the atomic bombings were not the last act of World War II,
而是对苏冷战的开始
but the first act of this cold war with Russia.
哪个物理学家
Which physicist?
你应该认识  帕特里克·布莱克特
I think you knew him. Patrick Blackett.
他可能是对的
He may not be wrong.
史汀生告诉我
Stimson is now telling me
我们轰炸了一个已经战败的敌人
we bombed an enemy that was essentially defeated.
罗伯特  你的影响力最大
Robert, you've all the influence now.
拜托
Please,
敦促他们让我继续研究氢弹
urge them to continue my research on the Super.
我做不到  也不会做  爱德华
I neither can nor will, Edward.
为什么
Why not?
我们不该把资源用在这里
It's not the right use of our resources.
你真的这么想吗
Is that what you really believe?
J·罗伯特·奥本海默  谜一样的原子大师
J. Robert Oppenheimer? Sphinx-like guru of the atom?
没人了解你的信仰
Nobody knows what you believe.
你自己知道吗
Do you?
最后一次
One final time,
计划负责人J·罗伯特·奥本海默博士
our program director, Dr. J. Robert Oppenheimer.
我希望  多年后
I hope that in years to come,
你们会骄傲地回想起自己在这里的工作
you will look back on your work here with pride.
但今天的主题不是骄傲  而是深切担忧
But today, that pride must be tempered with a profound concern.
如果在交战世界的武器库中加入核武器
If atomic weapons are to be added to the arsenals of a warring world,
那么人类总有一天
then the day will come
将咒骂洛斯阿拉莫斯这个名字
when people will curse the name of Los Alamos.
抱歉  上将
Sorry, Admiral.
路上买了这个
Stopped off to get this.
似乎对我们有利
Seems pretty favorable.
是奥本海默  注释写的什么
There's Oppenheimer. What's the caption?
"J·罗伯特·奥本海默  施特劳斯与他开战
"J. Robert Oppenheimer. Strauss fought him...
美国赢得胜利"
"and the US won."
这就够了
That'll work.
这是你那天说的话
Those were your words from the other day.
我们需要转换策略
We needed to pivot.
你怎么知道《时代》会这么写
But how would you know what Time Magazine was gonna write?
亨利·卢斯是我的朋友
Henry Luce is a friend.
你坐在这  让我给你讲  该怎么达到目的
You sat here and let me tell you how it's done,
而你早就开始布局了
but you've been far ahead all along.
要在华盛顿生存下来
Survival in Washington.
就要知道怎么达到目的
It's about knowing how to get things done.
对
Right.
你是怎么说波登的来着
What was it you said about Borden?
为什么要那么直接  让大家知道你是主使呢
Why get caught holding the knife yourself?
我现在觉得  波登是替你干脏活的
I'm beginning to think Borden was holding the knife for you.
现在关键在于
It's gonna come down to
波登对泰勒有多大影响
how much influence Borden's been able to exert on Teller.
我的话很好笑吗
Did I say something funny?
只念叨波登
Just "Borden, Borden, Borden",
但我们都明白施特劳斯才是幕后主使
when we all know that it's Strauss.
是路易斯把我带到普林斯顿的  吉蒂
Lewis brought me to Princeton, Kitty.
然后你在国会面前羞辱了他
And then you humiliated him in front of Congress.
但比三明治有用
But more useful than a sandwich!
我说得怎么样
How'd I do?
好得有点过了  罗伯特
Maybe a little too well, Robert.
那是六年前的事了
That was six years ago.
他们伺机而动  睚眦必报
You know, they're truly vindictive, patient as saints.
施特劳斯明确表示过他保持中立
Strauss has been perfectly clear that he is neutral.
醒醒吧  就是施特劳斯干的
Wake up! It is Strauss!
从始至终都是施特劳斯  你比谁都清楚
It's always been Strauss, and you know it!
你为什么不和他斗
Why won't you fight him?
不是尼科斯干的  也不是胡佛或者杜鲁门的手下
It wasn't Nichols, or Hoover, or one of Truman's guys.
而是你
It was you.
是你把文件给了波登
You gave the file to Borden.
你煽动他举报奥本海默
You set him on Oppenheimer.
-你说服了他  -波登
- You convinced him... - Borden...
根本不需要被说服
didn't take any convincing.
慢慢来  综合所有材料
Take your time, use the entire file.
把结论写下来  再交给联调局
Write up your conclusions, send them to the FBI.
材料是准备了一大堆
The material's obviously extensive,
但没什么新鲜料
but there's nothing new here.
所以才要你来写结论
Your conclusions will be.
这样他们就必须回答
And they'll have to be answered.
让胡佛再转给麦卡锡
Hoover passes them to McCarthy?
那个自吹自擂的笨蛋算计不过奥本海默
Oppenheimer's too slippery for that self-promoting clown.
我和胡佛谈过了
I've talked it over with Hoover.
他会拖住麦卡锡
He'll hold McCarthy at bay
同时你去面对原子能委员会
while you do this with the AEC.
-搞成庭审吗  -不  不能搞庭审
- Trial? - No, no trial.
你不能给奥本海默发挥的机会
You can't give Oppenheimer a platform.
不能让他悲情殉道
You can't martyr him.
我们必须彻彻底底地让奥本海默信誉扫地
We need a systematic destruction of Oppenheimer's credibility,
这样他就再也不能插手国家安全事务
so he can never again speak on matters of national security.
然后呢
Then what?
找个破旧的小房间  远离公众的视野
A shabby little room. Far from the limelight.
一个简单的官僚程序
A simple bureaucratic procedure.
他的安全许可快要到期了
His Q clearance. It's up for renewal.
你把指控信发给联调局
You send your accusations to the FBI...
胡佛再转发给原子能委员会
Hoover sends them to the AEC.
你被迫行动
You're forced to act.
写一份诉状
You write up an indictment.
然后告诉奥本海默
You tell Oppenheimer
他的许可到期不续了
his security clearance is not being renewed.
但给他一次上诉的机会
But offer him the chance to appeal.
如你所见  罗伯特  这份文件还没被签署
As you can see, Robert, it's not yet signed.
-我能留着吗  -不行
- May I keep this? - No.
如果你选择上诉
If you do decide to appeal,
他们才必须给你一份复件
they'll have to send you a copy.
等他上诉  而且信我的  他肯定会
When he appeals, and trust me, he will,
我就指派一个委员会
I appoint a board.
其中当然会有律师
They will, of course, have counsel.
-检察官吗  -有  不叫检察官而已
- Prosecutor? - In all but name.
-是谁  -罗杰·罗伯
- Who? - Roger Robb.
罗伯将有权查阅奥本海默的档案
Robb will have security clearance to examine Oppenheimer's file.
格雷委员会也有  但奥本海默的律师没有
As will the Gray Board. Defense counsel will not.
闭门听证会
A closed hearing.
在你们对我的起诉书中提到的所谓审讯信息
The so-called interrogatory information in your indictment of me...
没有旁听席和记者  无需举证
No audience, no reporters, no burden of proof.
无需举证
No burden of proof?
我们不是来定他罪的
We're not convicting.
我们是要搞垮他
We're just denying.
你怎么说的来着
What is it you said?
这只是游戏规则而已
This is just how the game is played.
请恕我天真
Well, forgive my naivete.
愚夫走到明处就被吞噬
Amateurs seek the sun, get eaten.
智者待在暗处观兵不动
Power stays in the shadows.
但您这次已经不能藏身于暗处了
But, sir, you're... you're out of the shadows now.
没错  所以我们的计划必须成功
Yeah, that's why this has to work.
泰勒今早出庭
Teller's testifying this morning.
还算有利  然后呢
That'll help. And then...
希尔下午出庭
Hill is in the afternoon.
希尔也会对我们有利
Hill is gonna help us too.
如你所见  罗伯特  这份文件还没被签署
As you can see, Robert, it's not yet signed.
-我能留着吗  -不行
- May I keep this? - No.
如果你选择上诉
If you do decide to appeal,
他们才必须给你一份复件
then they'll have to send you a copy.
让我的司机送你  别和我客气
Take my car and driver, I insist.
我要咨询我的律师  路易斯
I'll have to consult my lawyers, Lewis.
没问题  但别太久
Of course. But don't take too long.
尼科斯那边我也拖不了太久
I can't keep Nichols at bay.
罗伯特  我很抱歉事情弄到这步田地
I'm sorry it's come to this, Robert.
本不该这样的
I think it's wrong.
尼科斯希望我上诉
Nichols wants me to fight,
这样他就能把一切记录在案
so he can get it all on the record.
施特劳斯想让我放弃上诉
Strauss wants me to walk away.
施特劳斯吃准了你不会上诉
Strauss knows that you can't do that.
料定你会接受指控
You'd be accepting the charges.
这样你就会丢掉工作
You'll lose your job.
名誉扫地  我们连房子都保不住了
You will lose your reputation. We'll lose our house.
罗伯特  我们必须抗争
Robert, we have to fight.
作为原子能委员会的律师  我不能为你辩护
As AEC counsel, I can't represent you.
我会找劳埃德·加里森
I'll call Lloyd Garrison.
他很出色
Oh, he's good.
是最出色的
The best,
但我还是要提醒你
but I have to warn you.
这不是公平斗争
This won't be a fair fight.
1943年  你与鲍里斯·帕什的谈话中
During your interview with Boris Pash in 1943,
是否提到过缩微胶卷
did you refer to microfilm?
-没有  -11号文件  第1页  第3段
- No. - Tab 11, page one, paragraph three.
你从没说过  "领事馆的人
You never said, "man of the consulate,
用缩微胶卷的行家"
expert in the use of microfilm"?
-抱歉  打断一下  -不
- I'm sorry, I'm sorry... - No.
我想知道罗伯先生引用的是哪份文件
I would like to know what document Mr. Robb is quoting from,
能不能也给我们一份复件
and if we might be furnished with a copy.
这是保密文件  加里森先生
The document is classified, Mr. Garrison.
我觉得我们应该用第一手信息
I think we should get back to firsthand information.
这就是第一手信息
This is firsthand.
怎么确认的  罗杰
How so, Roger?
那次谈话被录音了
There was a recording of the interview.
你让我的委托人冒着做伪证的风险事无巨细地回忆
You let my client sit here and potentially perjure himself,
但其实你手里一直有一份录音
and all this time, you had a recording?
没人强迫你的委托人歪曲自己以前的言论
Nobody told your client to misrepresent his former answers.
歪曲  那可是12年前说的话
Misrepresent? It was 12 years ago!
我们可以听听录音吗
Can we hear this recording?
你没有听录音的权限  加里森先生
You don't have the clearance, Mr. Garrison.
那你读出来  它不就被记录在案了吗
But you're reading it into the record!
我来  我来
Please, please.
请问我们的质询是要诱供还是找真相
Is this proceeding interested in entrapment or in truth?
如果是真相  那公开透明呢
If it's truth, where's the disclosure?
有证人吗
Where's the witness list?
加里森先生  你很清楚我们这不是在法庭
Mr. Garrison, this isn't a trial, as you are well aware.
检方举证原则当下不适用
Evidentiary rules do not apply.
我们面临的是国家安全问题
We are dealing with national security.
我知道  先生  但恕我直言
Yes, sir, with all due respect,
我还是不能理解
I fail to see
为什么国家安全可以绕开庭审流程
how national security prevents the prosecution
连一份证人名单都不提供
from providing us with a list of witnesses!
也许我们该休会一下了
Perhaps we are in need of a brief recess.
先生们  我向你们保证
Gentlemen. You have my words.
如果你们说它是来自一份笔录  我接受
If you say they're from a transcript, then I'll accept it.
我都解释过了  那是我胡乱编造的
I've already explained I made up a cock-and-bull story.
胡乱编造的故事怎么可以这么详实
And why would anyone make up such an elaborate story?
因为我犯蠢了
Because I was an idiot.
为什么胡编
Why lie?
为的就是不把中间人
Well, clearly with the intention of not revealing
公之于众
who the intermediary was.
哈康·薛瓦利埃  你的那位共产党朋友
Your friend, Haakon Chevalier, the communist.
你们现在还是朋友么
Is he still your friend?
是
Yes.
拉比博士  感谢你能来
Dr. Rabi, thank you for coming.
你知道他们还传唤了谁吗
You know who else the prosecution has called?
泰勒  明摆着的
Teller, obviously.
他们肯定问了劳伦斯
They've asked Lawrence.
他怎么说的
What did he say?
他本来是想站在你这边的
He wasn't going to help them,
-但是  -但是什么
- but... - But?
施特劳斯告诉他
Strauss told him that
你和露丝·托尔曼有染好多年了
you and Ruth Tolman had been having an affair for years.
从你和他们一起住在帕萨迪纳时就开始了
The whole time you lived with them in Pasadena.
他让劳伦斯相信
He convinced Lawrence that
理查德就是因为这个伤心过世
Richard died of a broken heart.
-无稽之谈  -哪里无稽
- That's absurd. - What part?
伤心过世
A broken heart.
理查德根本就蒙在鼓里
Richard never found out.
劳伦斯也来作证吗
Is Lawrence gonna testify?
我不确定
I don't know.
拉比博士  你目前担任什么公职
Dr. Rabi, what governmental positions do you currently hold?
我接替了奥本海默博士
I am the chairman of the general advisory committee to the AEC,
担任原子能委员会的顾问委员会主席
succeeding Dr. Oppenheimer.
你和奥本海默博士相识多久了
And how long have you known Dr. Oppenheimer?
1928年认识的
Since 1928.
我对他十分了解
I... I know him quite well.
了解到足以评价他的人格品性吗
Well enough to speak to the bearing of his loyalty and character?
奥本海默博士品行正直
Dr. Oppenheimer is a man of upstanding character.
对于祖国和朋友  以及他的工作机构
And he is loyal to the United States, to his friends,
都无比的忠诚
to the institutions of which he is part.
吃吧
Eat.
刚才是谁
Who was that?
没谁  别担心
Nothing to worry about.
苏联人试爆了原子弹后
After the Russian A-bomb test,
劳伦斯博士找你讨论过氢弹的事吗
did Dr. Lawrence come to see you about the hydrogen bomb?
那你最好去问他
You'd be better off asking him.
我自然要问
Well, I fully intend to.
你认为奥本海默博士
Would you say that Dr. Oppenheimer
坚决反对氢弹么
was unalterably opposed to the H-bomb?
不  他认为开启氢弹这种核聚变项目
No, he, he thought that a fusion program
要以停止正在顺利进行的核裂变项目为代价
would come at the expense of our awfully good fission program.
但事实并非如此
But that proved not to be the case.
事实上  二者可以共存
In the event, both could be done.
假设本委员会
Suppose that this board did not feel satisfied
最终无法认定
that in his testimony here
奥本海默博士是诚实可信的
Dr. Oppenheimer had been wholly truthful,
你对他的清白与否持何观点呢
what would you say whether or not he should be cleared?
一个完成了奥本海默这般成就的人
Why go through all this against a man
我们为什么还要如此对待他
who has accomplished what Dr. Oppenheimer has?
看看他的履历
Look at his record.
我们拥有了原子弹  一系列原子弹
We have an A-bomb, and a whole series of it.
一系列氢弹
We have a whole series of super bombs.
你们还苛求什么
What more do you want?
来条美人鱼
Mermaids?
我和施特劳斯部长相识多年
But I've known Secretary Strauss for many years.
我认为有必要提及
And I feel it a necessity to express the warm support
路易斯对科学和科学家的暖心支持
for science and scientists Lewis has shown.
没什么急事的话我们先午休吧
We'll break now. Unless there's any immediate business.
议员先生  我想再次提请
Senator, I'd like to once again request
一份证人名单
that we're furnished with a list of witnesses.
我要提醒候选人
And I will remind the nominee
我们一般不会提前知晓证人的信息
that we don't always have that information in advance.
我们确认的是希尔博士午饭后会出庭
We do know that Dr. Hill will be here after lunch.
主席先生  我们下一位证人劳伦斯博士
Mr. Chairman, our next scheduled witness, Dr. Lawrence,
可能是由于结肠炎的原因不能来了
has apparently come down with colitis.
所以我们递补传唤了威廉·波登
So we'll proceed with William Borden instead.
波登先生  欢迎前来  请坐
Mr. Borden, welcome. Please take a seat.
波登先生
Mr. Borden,
在你调查奥本海默博士期间
during your investigation into Dr. Oppenheimer,
是否得出了最终结论
did you reach certain conclusions?
-是的  -你是否以信件的形式
- I did. - And did there come a time
把调查结果寄给了
when you expressed those conclusions in a letter
联邦调查局局长J·埃德加·胡佛先生
to Mr. J. Edgar Hoover, of the Federal Bureau of Investigation?
是的
That is correct.
写信之前
Prior to the writing of the letter,
你是否和任何原子能委员会的人讨论过
did you discuss the writing of the letter
写信本身这件事
with anybody attached to the Atomic Energy Commission?
-从没有  -很好
- I did not. - Excellent.
-你拿到信的复件了吗  -就在我面前
- Do you have a copy of the letter? - I have one in front of me.
能请你诵读一下吗
Would you please be so kind as to read it, sir?
"尊敬的胡佛先生  我写这封信是为了阐述..."
"Dear Mr. Hoover, the purpose of this letter is to state...
抱歉  我能问下吗
I'm sorry, I'm sorry, if I could have...
为什么要打断他
What is the purpose of the delay?
他不过是念他写的信
He's simply going to read the letter.
主席先生  我是第一次见到这封信
Mr. Chairman, this is the first I've seen of this letter.
光扫一眼就看到很多说法  其中至少有一条
And I see statements here, at least one,
是那种我觉得在座的各位
of a kind that I don't think
都不会愿意写入会议记录的
anyone would like to see go into the record.
这些指控都是之前没有的
These are accusations that have not previously been made,
没有一个来自尼科斯的起诉书
that are not part of the indictment from Nichols.
不应该在这里讨论的指控
Accusations of a kind that I don't think belong here.
信是证人主动写的
The witness wrote this letter on his own initiative,
列举的证据也都是本委员会之前就知道的
laying out evidence that has already been before the board.
他的结论是有效力的证词
His conclusions are valid testimony,
就像奥本海默博士的朋友们做出的正面评价一样
just like the positive conclusions of friends of Dr. Oppenheimer.
有正面就有负面
It cuts both ways.
控方律师持有这封信有多久了
How long has counsel been in possession of this letter?
我并不认为我需要接受你的盘问
I don't think I should be subject to cross-examination by you,
加里森先生
Mr. Garrison.
加里森先生  鉴于委员会成员皆已读过这封信
Mr. Garrison, given that we on the board have all read the letter,
把它记录在案不好吗
wouldn't it be better to have it in the record?
我们继续
Let's proceed.
"尊敬的胡佛先生
"Dear Mr. Hoover,
我写这封信是为了阐述我的以下意见
"the purpose of this letter is to state my opinion,
基于数年对于现有机密证据的研究
"based upon years of study of the available classified evidence,
我认为J·罗伯特·奥本海默
"that, more probably than not,
有可能是一名苏联间谍
"J. Robert Oppenheimer is an agent of the Soviet Union.
证据列出如下
"The following conclusions are justified.
一  1929年至1942年间
"One, between 1929 and 1942, more probably than not,
J·罗伯特·奥本海默有可能是一个坚定的共产主义者
"J. Robert Oppenheimer was a sufficiently hardened communist
并因此自愿为苏联提供情报
"that he volunteered information to the Soviets.
二  他有可能
"Two, more probably than not,
自那时起就作为一名间谍存在
"he has since been functioning as an espionage agent.
三
"Three.
他有可能受苏联上级指示
"More probably than not, he has since acted under a Soviet directive
自那时起影响美国的军事政策"
"in influencing United States military policy."
-对不起  罗伯特  -"原子能  情报及..."
- I'm sorry, Robert. - "Atomic energy, intelligence and..."
到底有没有人能说出事情的真相
Is anyone ever going to tell the truth about what's happening here?
现在请大卫·希尔博士发言
We will now hear from Dr. David Hill.
希尔博士  请发表你的看法
Dr. Hill, would you care to make a statement?
谢谢
Thank you.
我受邀为路易斯·施特劳斯作证
I've been asked to testify about Lewis Strauss,
他已在政府部门
a man who has given years of service
久居高位
in high positions of government,
他素来有认真  勤奋  聪慧之名
and who is known to be earnest, hard-working, and intelligent.
以下完全是我本人的真实想法
The views I have to express are my own,
我相信我要说的会帮助诸位了解
but I believe that much I have to say will help to indicate why
我国绝大多数科学家希望施特劳斯先生
most of the scientists in this country would prefer to see Mr. Strauss
彻底离开政府部门的原因
completely out of government.
您指的是某些科学家针对施特劳斯先生的敌意
You're referring to the hostility of certain scientists,
只因为他在奥本海默事件中
directed toward Mr. Strauss, because of his commitment to security,
选择了国家安全
as demonstrated in the Oppenheimer affair?
不是
No.
是因为他对奥本海默博士本人
Because of the personal vindictiveness
表现出的报复心理
he demonstrated against Dr. Oppenheimer.
肃静  肃静
Order! Order!
在这个国家的大多数科学家看来
It appears to most scientists around this country
罗伯特·奥本海默现在正遭受抨击  历经磨难
that Robert Oppenheimer is now being pilloried,
只是因为他表达了自己的诚实观点
and put through an ordeal, because he expressed his honest opinions.
布什博士  我认为这场听证会只是
Dr. Bush, I thought I was performing a service to my country
-我在尽对国家的义务  -本国不该有任何委员会
- when hearing this case. - No board, in this country,
可以只是因为他表达强烈意见
should sit in judgment of a man
就对他进行审判
because he expressed his strong opinions.
如果要进行这种审判  先审判我吧
If you want to try that case, you should try me.
不好意思  先生们  我可能太激动了
Excuse me, gentlemen, if I've... become stirred.
但我就是很激动
But I am.
希尔博士  我们已经知道
Dr. Hill, we've already heard that
施特劳斯先生并没有提起
Mr. Strauss did not bring the charges,
或者参与到对奥本海默博士的听证会中
or participate in the hearings against Dr. Oppenheimer.
奥本海默事件...
The Oppenheimer matter was...
很大程度上是由路易斯·施特劳斯
initiated, and carried through, largely through
对奥本海默的敌意引发并进行下去的
the animus of Lewis Strauss.
奥本海默把施特劳斯关于向挪威出口同位素的立场
Oppenheimer made mincemeat out of Strauss's position
驳得体无完肤
on the shipments of isotopes to Norway,
施特劳斯一直没有原谅这场公开的奇耻大辱
and Strauss never forgave him this public humiliation.
他们之间的另一个冲突
Another controversy between them
是他们对于氢弹
centered around their differences in judgment
在国防方面作用的意见分歧
on how the H-bomb would contribute to national security.
施特劳斯试图利用人员安全系统
Strauss turned to the personnel security system in order to
以压制奥本海默的影响力
destroy Oppenheimer's effectiveness,
施特劳斯找到了一些有野心的人
and Strauss was able to find a few ambitious men
他们同样反对奥本海默的观点  并且嫉妒他
who also disagreed with Oppenheimer's positions and envied him
嫉妒他在政界的声誉
his prestige in government circles.
我一直认为  到现在仍然认为
I've always assumed, and still assume,
他忠于美国
that he is loyal to the United States.
我坚信  也会继续坚信这一点
I believe this, and I shall believe it,
除非我看到非常确凿的反驳证据
until I see very conclusive proof to the opposite.
你认为奥本海默博士是安全风险吗
Do you or do you not believe that Dr. Oppenheimer is a security risk?
有很多次  我观察到奥本海默博士
In a great number of cases, I have seen Dr. Oppenheimer act in a way
以一种我很难理解的方式行事
which was, to me, exceedingly hard to understand.
我在很多问题上完全不同意他的观点
I thoroughly disagreed with him in numerous issues,
他的行为对我来说其实是迷惑而混乱的
and his actions frankly appeared to me confused and complicated.
因此  我希望看到
To this extent, I feel I want to see
这个国家的核心利益
the vital interests of this country
掌握在我更加了解  因此也更加信任的人手中
in hands which I understand better, and therefore trust more.
-谢谢你  博士  -谢谢
- Thank you, Doctor. - Thank you.
对不起
I'm sorry.
你居然跟他握手了
You shook his fucking hand!?
要是我就啐他一脸
I would have spit in his face.
委员会大概不会想看到那种场景
I'm not sure the Board would have appreciated that.
对你来说不够绅士吗
Is it not gentlemanly enough for you?
我倒觉得你们就是太绅士了
I think you're all being too goddamn gentlemanly.
格雷肯定知道罗伯在做什么
Gray must see what Robb is doing.
为什么不阻止他
Why doesn't he just shut him down?
还有你  居然跟泰勒握手
And you, shaking Teller's hand.
你别再沉迷于你的殉道者角色了
You need to stop playing the martyr.
按照现行的原子能委员会准则
Under the current AEC guidelines,
你今天还会给奥本海默博士发放安全许可吗
would you clear Dr. Oppenheimer today?
根据我对《原子能法》的理解
Under my interpretation of the Atomic Energy Act,
虽然1942年我聘请奥本海默博士时这法案还不存在
which did not exist when I hired Dr. Oppenheimer in 1942,
但如果我今天是委员会成员
I would not clear him today
不会批准他的安全许可
if I were on the commission.
好的  谢谢你  将军  问话结束了
Good. Thank you, General. That is all.
但我也不会批准其中任何人的
But I don't think I'd clear any of those guys.
结束了
That's all.
奥本海默博士与克劳斯·福克斯的选任
Dr. Oppenheimer had no responsibility in the selection
以及安全许可没有任何关系  对吗
or the clearance of Klaus Fuchs, did he?
对的  完全没有
No. None at all.
你也不想让委员会觉得
And you wouldn't want to leave this board
你今天所说的任何内容是在质疑
with any suggestion today that
他在洛斯阿拉莫斯工作期间
you're here questioning his basic loyalty to the United States
对美国的忠诚  对吧
in the operation of Los Alamos?
绝对没有
By no means.
我希望我没有给任何人留下一丝这种印象
I hope I didn't lead anyone to believe otherwise for an instant.
谢谢你  将军
Thank you, General.
-好了  我们别让他们等了  -她会来的
- Okay. We shouldn't keep them waiting. - She'll be here.
你真的希望她出席吗
Do you even want her here?
只有傻瓜或者不成熟的人
Only a fool or an adolescent presumes
才会自认为了解别人的伴侣关系
to know someone else's relationship,
你应该都不是吧  劳埃德
and you're neither, Lloyd.
吉蒂和我都是成年人
Kitty and I are grown-ups.
我们共同经历过考验
We've walked through fire together.
她可以的
She'll do fine.
你对共产主义的看法是赞成  反对还是中立
Would you describe your views on communism as pro, anti, neutral?
非常反对
Very strongly against.
我跟共产主义没有任何关系  从...
I've had nothing to do with communism in, since...
从1936年...
since 1936. Since...
在我遇见罗伯特之前
Since before I met Robert.
我的问话结束
That's all.
记录表明  奥本海默没有受到格雷委员会
The record demonstrates that Oppenheimer was not interrogated
公正无私的讯问
by impartial and disinterested counsel for the Gray Board.
检察官使用了所有的
He was interrogated by a prosecutor who used
法律范围内允许的审讯技巧
all the tricks of a rather ingenious legal background.
你在指控格雷委员会进行的是一场检控
You are charging now that the Gray Board permitted a prosecution.
如果我是格雷委员会的一员
If I were on the Gray Board,
我会对实际作为检方的人
I would have protested against the tactics
使用的手段提出异议
of the man who served in fact as the prosecuting counsel.
他并不是委员会指派的人
A man appointed not by the Board,
而是路易斯·施特劳斯指派的
but by Lewis Strauss.
他是谁
Who was this?
不好意思
I'm sorry?
他是谁
Who was this?
罗杰·罗伯
Roger Robb.
奥本海默夫人
Mrs. Oppenheimer.
你有没有共产党员卡片
Did you have a Communist Party membership card?
我...我不确定
I'm... I'm not sure.
不确定
Not sure?
入党的途径想必是需要寄一些钱过去
I mean, presumably, the act of joining the party
然后收到一张卡片  没错吧
required sending some money and receiving a card, no?
对不起
Sorry.
没错
Yes.
只是这件事过去太久太久了  不是吗  罗伯先生
It's just, it was all so very long ago, Mr. Robb, wasn't it?
-也不是吧  -久到让人忘记了
- Not really. - Long enough to have forgotten.
你把卡片还回去了吗  还是撕掉了
Did you return the card, or rip it up?
你说的是我都不记得有过的那张卡片吗
The card whose existence I've forgotten?
-你的共产党员卡吗  -没有一点印象
- Your Communist Party membership card? - Haven't the slightest idea.
你能区分苏联共产主义和共产主义吗
Can a distinction be made between Soviet communism and communism?
在我还是党员时
In the days when I was a member,
我认为二者是完全不同的
I thought they were definitely two things.
我认为美国共产党
I thought that the Communist Party of the United States
关心的是国内的问题
was concerned with our domestic problems.
我现在不相信这点了
I now no longer believe this.
我认为一切都联系了起来
I believe the whole thing's linked together
向全世界扩散开去
and spread all over the world,
我16年前退党以后  一直坚信这一点
and I have believed this since I left the party 16 years ago.
-但是...  -17年前  我记错了
- But... - 17 years ago. My mistake.
-但你...  -抱歉  是18
- But you... - Sorry, 18.
18年前
18 years ago.
你是否清楚你的丈夫直到1942年
Are you familiar with the fact your husband was making contributions
都还在为西班牙内战出力
to the Spanish Civil War as late as 1942?
我知道罗伯特会时不时往外汇款
I knew that Robert gave money from time to time.
你知道这些钱会流入共产党的渠道吗
Did you know this money was going into Communist Party channels?
-你是说经过吗  -你说什么
- Don't you mean through? - Pardon?
你应该是想说钱会经过共产党的渠道  对吧
I think you mean through Communist Party channels, don't you?
-对  -是吗
- Yes. - Yes?
-是的  -好的
- Yes. - Yes.
那这是否意味着直至1942年
Then would it be fair to say that this meant that by 1942,
你的丈夫还没有停止
your husband had not stopped
与共产党的瓜葛呢
having anything to do with the Communist Party?
你不用只回答是或否
You don't have to answer that yes or no,
你可以按照你的想法回答
you can answer that any way you wish.
我知道  谢谢  你的提问有问题
I know that, thank you. It's your question.
表述得不太到位
It's not properly phrased.
-你知道我想问什么吗  -我知道
- Do you understand what I'm getting at? - I do.
那为什么不按照那个来回答呢
Then why don't you answer it that way?
因为我不喜欢你的措辞
Because I don't like your phrase,
"与共产党的瓜葛"
"having anything to do with the Communist Party,"
因为罗伯特和共产党
because Robert never had anything to do
从来没有任何关系
with the Communist Party as such.
我知道他给西班牙难民捐款
I know he gave money to Spanish refugees.
我知道他对共产主义思想很感兴趣
I know he took an intellectual interest in communist ideas.
有两种共产主义者吗
Are there two types of communists?
思想共产主义者  以及你们普通的共产主义者
Intellectual communists, and your plain old regular commie?
我回答不了这个问题
I couldn't answer that one.
我也不能
I couldn't either.
晚安
Good evening.
罗伯特  你赢不了
Robert, you can't win this thing.
这是一个有着预定结果的袋鼠法庭[无视公平正义和司法程序]It's a kangaroo court with a predetermined outcome.
为什么还要让自己经历这些呢
Why put yourself through more of it?
我有我的原因
I have my reasons.
好吧
Alright.
晚安
Good night.
他说得有道理
He has a point.
-我觉得你不理解  阿尔伯特  -是吗
- I'm not sure you understand, Albert. - No?
我离开了我的祖国  再没回去
I left my country, never to return.
你对你的祖国尽职尽责
You served your country well.
如果这就是她给你的回报...
If this is the reward she offers you, then...
或许你应该考虑放弃她
perhaps you should turn your back on her.
不巧  我非常热爱这个国家
Damn it, I happen to love this country.
那就让他们见鬼去吧
Then tell them to go to hell.
好了  再也没有什么确认听证会
Interestingly enough, this is no longer a confirmation hearing.
现在  这就是审判
It's now a trial...
关于一场审判的审判
about a trial!
我的老天啊
For god's sakes!
情况不太妙  他告诉大家是你发起的听证会
It's not good he's telling everyone you initiated the hearings.
他什么都没法证明
He can't prove a goddamn thing.
他绝对无法证明是我把文件给了波登
He certainly can't prove that I gave the file to Borden.
我们不是在法庭  先生  无需举证
We're not in court, sir. There's no burden of proof.
没错  他们不是来定罪的
Right, they're not convicting.
是要搞垮我
They're just denying.
希尔为什么会来诋毁我  他是出于什么目的
Why would Hill come here to tear me down? What's his angle?
见义当为需要理由吗
Do people need a reason to do the right thing?
-在他看来  -我告诉过你
- As he sees it. - I told you.
从第一次见面起  奥本海默就一直怂恿
Oppenheimer's been poisoning the scientists against me
科学家们跟我对着干
right from that first meeting.
我不知道那天奥本海默对他说了什么
I don't know what Oppenheimer said to him that day,
但爱因斯坦甚至都不愿拿正眼看我
but Einstein wouldn't even meet my eye.
奥本海默很擅长操纵同僚
Oppenheimer knows how to manipulate his own.
在洛斯阿拉莫斯
At Los Alamos,
他就利用过那些科学家的天真
he preyed on the naivete of scientists
他们以为有权决定我们如何使用其研究成果
who thought they get a say in how we use their work.
他们绝对想不到  他本人其实那样幼稚无知
They'll never think he was that naive himself.
博士  在氢弹研究的过程中
Doctor, during your work on the hydrogen bomb,
你是否曾因道义上的不安而止步不前
were you... deterred by any moral qualms?
是的  当然
Yes, of course.
但你还是继续研究下去了  对不对
But you still got on with your work, didn't you?
对  因为我做的是科学探索
Yes, because this was work of exploration,
不是武器研制
it was not the preparation of a weapon.
你是说这更像种学术涉猎
You mean it was more of an academic excursion?
不  如果能造出氢弹
No, it is not an academic thing,
就不是学术了
whether you can build a hydrogen bomb.
而是生死攸关的大事
It's a matter of life and death.
你在1942年
By 1942, you were actively pushing
曾积极推动氢弹研制  不是吗
the development of the hydrogen bomb, weren't you?
"推动"这个词不恰当
Pushing is not the right word.
是支持并参与研究
Supporting it and working on it, yes.
那这种道义上的不安是何时变得如此强烈
So when did these moral qualms become so strong
强到让你积极反对氢弹研制
that you actively opposed the development of the hydrogen bomb?
当有人说美国的政策是
When it was suggested that it be the policy of the United States
不惜一切代价制造出这些武器
to make these things at all costs,
而不考虑这些武器
without regard to the balance between these weapons
和我们的武器库中已有的核武器之间的平衡
and atomic weapons as part of our arsenal.
这与道义上的不安有什么关系
What do moral qualms have to do with that?
-与道义上的不安有什么关系  -对
- What do moral qualms have to do with it? - Yes.
奥本海默想独占原子弹
Oppenheimer wanted to own the atomic bomb.
他想成为撼动地球之人
He wanted to be The Man Who Moved the Earth.
他现在说要把"核妖魔"关回瓶中
He talks about putting the nuclear genie back in the bottle.
告诉你吧  我非常清楚
Well, I'm here to tell you that I know,
如果能重头来过  J·罗伯特·奥本海默
J. Robert Oppenheimer, if he could do it all over,
还是会做出相同选择
he'd do it all the same.
知道吗  他从未说过对轰炸广岛感到后悔
You know he's never once said that he regrets Hiroshima?
他还是会这么做  为什么
He'd do it all over. Why?
因为这让他成为有史以来最重要的人
Because it made him the most important man who ever lived.
我们不加限制地使用原子弹
We freely used the atomic bomb.
博士  事实上你协助选择了
In fact, Doctor, you assisted in selecting the target
在日本投放原子弹的目标  不是吗
to drop the atomic bomb on Japan, didn't you?
-对...  -那你知道  对吧
- Yes... - Well then, you knew, did you not,
向你选择的目标投放原子弹
that by dropping that atomic bomb on the target you selected,
会有成千上万的平民伤亡
that thousands of civilians would be killed or injured.
对吗
Is that correct?
对  我没想到会有那么多
Yes, not as many as turned out.
那有多少人伤亡
Oh. Then how many were killed or injured?
-七万人  -七万人  广岛和...
- 70,000. - 70,000, both Hiroshima and...
-总计十一万人  -轰炸当天的伤亡人数吗
- 110,000 to both. - On the day of each bombing?
对
Yes.
轰炸数周及数年以后呢
And in the weeks and years that followed?
估计有五至十万人
It has been put at somewhere between 50,000 and 100,000.
至少有二十二万人死亡
220,000 dead, at least.
-是的  -对此你会良心有愧吗
- Yes. - Any moral scruples about that?
备受煎熬
Terrible ones.
但你却在这里言之凿凿
But yet you testified in here
说轰炸广岛非常成功
that the bombing of Hiroshima was very successful.
-技术上很成功  -技术上非常成功
- Technically successful. - Oh! Technically it was very successful.
据说这加速了战争的结束
And it is also alleged to have helped to end the war.
你会支持
Would you have been supportive
向广岛投放氢弹吗
of the dropping of a hydrogen bomb on Hiroshima?
这根本没有意义
That would make no sense at all.
-为什么  -目标太小
- Why? - The target is too small.
假设日本有足够大的
Well, supposing there had been a target in Japan
可以投放热核武器的目标
big enough for a thermonuclear weapon,
你会反对投放吗
would you have been opposed to the dropping of it?
我当时没遇到这样的问题
This was not a problem with which I was confronted.
那我现在问你  先生
Well, I'm confronting you with it now, sir.
这都是他计划的一部分
It was all part of his plan.
他想要那种荣耀  自大  不真诚的负罪感
He wanted the glorious, insincere guilt of the self-important
像王冠一样戴在头上  并说
to wear like a fucking crown and say,
"不  我们不能走上这条路"
"No, we cannot go down this road,"
即使他知道我们不得不这样做
even as he knew we'd have to.
你会因为道德顾虑
Would you have been opposed to the dropping
反对向日本投放热核武器吗
of a thermonuclear weapon on Japan because of moral scruples?
是的  我想我会  先生
Yes, I believe I would, sir.
你反对向广岛投放原子弹
Did you oppose the dropping of an atomic bomb on Hiroshima
是因为道德顾虑吗
because of moral scruples?
-我们阐述了我们的...  -不  你你你你
- We set forth our... - No, you, you, you, you!
-我问的是你...  -我阐...
- I'm asking you... - I set...
-你你你  -我阐述了我们
- You, you, you! - I set forth our arguments
反对投放的理由  但我并不支持不投
against dropping it, but I did not endorse them.
你是说日以继夜工作三年
You mean after working night and day
造出原子弹后
for three years building the bomb,
你却反对使用它
you then argued against the use of it?
战争部长当时询问我
I was asked by the Secretary of War
科学家们的看法
what the views of scientists were.
我告诉了他们反对和赞成的意见
I gave them the views against and the views for.
你赞成向日本投放
You supported the dropping of the atom bomb
-原子弹  对吗  -你什么意思...
- on Japan, didn't you? - What do you mean...
-你赞成...  -你说"赞成"是什么意思
- You supported it... - What do you mean, support?
你帮助选择了目标  不是吗
Well, you helped pick the target, didn't you?
我是公事公办  我在洛斯阿拉莫斯没有决策权
I did my job. I was not in a policy-making position at Los Alamos.
命令我做什么我就做什么
I would have done anything I was asked to do.
那你本来也该造出氢弹的  不是吗
Well, then, you would have built the H-bomb too, wouldn't you?
-但我没法...  -我没问你这个  博士
- But I couldn't... - I didn't ask you that, Doctor!
苏联核试验后  你与人合署的
And the GAC report, which you co-authored
总顾问委员会报告上写道
after the Soviet atomic test said:
"永远不该造出氢弹"
"A super bomb should never be built!"
我们的意思是  我的意思是...
What we meant, what I meant...
-"我们"是谁  -听着  我的意思是...
- What you, who? - Look, what I meant...
谁
Who?
苏联人难道不会尽全力增强自己的军事实力吗
Well, wouldn't the Russians do anything to increase their strength?
如果我们造出来了  他们就必须造出来
If we did it, they would have to do it!
我们的努力只会让他们更努力
Our efforts would only fuel their efforts,
就像原子弹那样
just as it had with the atomic bomb!
没错  就像原子弹那样
Just as it had with the atomic bomb, exactly!
1945年毫无道德顾虑  1949年顾虑重重
No moral scruples in 1945, plenty in 1949.
奥本海默博士...
Dr. Oppenheimer...
你对氢弹强烈的道德感
when did your strong moral convictions develop
是什么时候形成的
with respect to the hydrogen bomb?
当我明白
When it became clear to me
我们会动用手中的任何武器时
that we would tend to use any weapon we had.
殉道者J·罗伯特·奥本海默
J. Robert Oppenheimer the martyr,
我正好满足了他的心愿
I gave him exactly what he wanted.
因"三位一体"而被世人铭记
To be remembered for Trinity,
不是因为广岛
not Hiroshima!
也不是因为长崎
Not Nagasaki!
他应该感谢我
He should be thanking me.
他并不
Well, he's not.
我们的票数还够吗
Do we still have enough votes?
还是我职业生涯的巅峰时刻
Or is the crowning moment of my career
即将成为我人生中最大的公开羞辱
about to become the most public humiliation of my life?
参议院全体议员即将投票
Full Senate's about to vote.
你会勉强通过
You'll scrape through.
很好  那召集媒体吧
Great, then gather the fucking press.
J·罗伯特·奥本海默博士
Dr. J. Robert Oppenheimer,
本委员会听取了你
this board, having heard testimony from you
及你的许多前同事和现同事的证词
and many of your current and former colleagues,
我们得出一致结论  你是个忠诚的公民
has come to the unanimous conclusion that you are a loyal citizen.
然而...
However...
鉴于你一直与共党分子牵扯不清
In the light of your continuing associations,
以及你对本国安全机构的漠视
and disregard for the security apparatus of this country,
外加你在氢弹项目上
together with your somewhat disturbing conduct
令人不安的行为
on the hydrogen bomb program,
并且很遗憾  你对本委员会的
and the regrettable lack of candor
一些回应缺乏坦诚
in certain of your responses to this board,
经过投票  2比1
we have voted, two-to-one,
我们拒绝延长你的安全许可
to deny the renewal of your security clearance.
完整的书面意见  包括埃文斯先生的异议
A full written opinion, with a dissent from Mr. Evans,
几天后将呈交原子能委员会
will be issued to the AEC in the coming days.
会议结束
That is all.
罗伯特  罗伯特
Robert. Robert.
别...
Don't...
别收床单
Don't take in the sheets.
两分钟  就两分钟
Two minutes. Two minutes!
会让你们拍的
You'll get your shot!
正式宣布了吗
Is it official?
有几个意料之外的反对者
Well, there were a couple of unexpected holdouts.
我被否决了  对吗
I'm denied. Yeah?
-恐怕是的  先生  -好吧
- I'm afraid so, sir. - Alright.
反对者有谁
Who were the holdouts?
有三位
Um, there were three.
以马萨诸塞州的新晋参议员为首
Led by the junior senator from Massachusetts.
一个想出名的年轻人
Young guy trying to make a name for himself,
不喜欢你对奥本海默所做的事
didn't like what you did to Oppenheimer.
他叫什么
What's his name?
肯尼迪
Uh, Kennedy.
约翰·F·肯尼迪
John F. Kennedy.
吉蒂
Kitty?
你以为任由他们肆意凌虐你
Did you think that if you let them tar and feather you,
全世界就会原谅你吗
then the world would forgive you?
不会的
It won't.
我们走着瞧
We'll see.
你说我会没事的
You told me I'd be okay.
对  但你没把所有事告诉我  对吗
Yeah, well, I didn't have all the facts, did I?
事实上
Here's a fact.
艾森豪威尔总统去年亲手在我胸前
President Eisenhower pinned the Medal of Freedom
别上自由勋章
on my chest last year,
因为我做的都是利国利民的事
because I've always done what's right for this country.
他们不希望我进入内阁  没...  没关系
They don't want me in the cabinet room? Well, that's... that's fine.
也许他们应该转而邀请奥本海默
Maybe they should just invite Oppenheimer instead.
也许他们会的
Maybe they will.
我告诉过你  他唆使那些科学家反对我
I told you. He turned the scientists against me,
从爱因斯坦开始  一个接着一个
one by one, starting with Einstein.
我跟你说过  爱因斯坦  爱因斯坦在池塘边
I told you about that. Einstein. Einstein by the pond.
是的  但先生  既然没人...
You did, but you know, sir, since nobody...
真正知道他们那天到底聊了什么
really knows what they said to each other that day,
有没有可能他们根本没说起你
is it possible they didn't talk about you at all?
有没有可能他们聊的是...
Is it possible they spoke about something, uh...
更重要的事
more important?
施特劳斯先生  看这里  施特劳斯先生
Mr. Strauss. Over here! Mr. Strauss!
谢谢
Thank you.
阿尔伯特
Albert.
当下风云人物
The man of the moment.
你曾在伯克利为我办过一场招待会
You once held a reception for me in Berkeley.
-你给我颁了奖  -是的
- You gave me an award, hmm? - Yes.
你们都以为我已无法理解
You all thought that I had lost the ability
我所开创的领域
to understand what I'd started.
所以...
So...
那个奖不是颁给我的  是给你们的  对吗
The award really wasn't for me, it was for all of you, hmm?
现在轮到你
Now it's your turn
来解决自己的成就带来的问题
to deal with the consequences of your achievement.
终有一天  等他们对你惩罚够了
And one day, when they've punished you enough,
就会给你奉上三文鱼和土豆沙拉
they'll serve you salmon and potato salad.
演讲称颂你
Make speeches.
给你颁奖
Give you a medal.
你好  弗兰克
Hello, Frank.
你幸福  我就幸福
You're happy, I'm happy.
拍着你的背告诉你  一切都过去了
Pat you on the back, tell you all is forgiven.
记住...
Just remember...
那些都不是为了你
it won't be for you.
而是为了他们自己
It'll be for them.
阿尔伯特...
Albert...
当我带着那些计算结果去找你时
when I came to you with those calculations,
我们都以为我们可能会触发
we thought we might start a chain reaction
摧毁整个世界的链式反应
that would destroy the entire world.
我记得  怎么了
I remember it well. What of it?
我想我们触发了
I believe we did.